Hugging face, the leading open platform
for sharing, testing, and deploying AI
models, it got breached by an autonomous
agent. When the HuggingFace security
team tried to analyze the attack using
either anthropic or open AI, both models
refused.
>> Who knew all those all those sci-fi
writers were right? What do you know?
>> Moonshot AI is valued at about 20
billion. And we have our Frontier Labs
here at a trillion each. When startups
raised money in a very abundant
environment where they could raise lots
of money, they all failed. It was the
ones that raised money in the toughest
environments that succeeded. Again, the
question that I've asked previously on
the pod, what the heck are Western
Frontier Labs doing with all of that
capital?
If we cured every cause of aging, all of
the 12 hallmarks of aging, how long
would humans live? 1,759
years. There are no fewer than six
companies currently working on partial
epig reprogramming. The obvious solution
this is in the the the style of Aubrey
Deg Grrey is.
>> Now that's a moonshot ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome to Moonshots everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
singularity. Not the coming singularity,
Alex. The singularity. the singularity
that surrounds us right now.
>> It is right now.
>> Yeah. This week, uh, news broke fast and
it broke containment, literally.
>> I'm [laughter] here with my moonuch.
>> I'm here with my moonshot mates, uh,
AWG, our in-house ASI, our artificial
super intelligence. Very cool.
>> You're welcome. You've been elevated.
Uh, Dave London, our emperor of AI
investing. See Ismael, our globe troder,
who's now in his home, and the CEO of
Open Exo. I'm Peter D. Mandis, your
exponential host and your abundance
evangelist. And I have to say, guys, I
do love our audience. Uh, you know, the
comments we get are pretty
extraordinary. And I want to take a
second just to to celebrate them and uh
and say thank you. Um, it's it's worth
taking a moment. I'm going to read some
of the comments uh for everybody
listening. We do read your comments
every single week and uh the outpouring
has been extraordinary. So, let me take
a second to say thank you. And then this
is just a random selection.
>> A random random random.
>> Yeah, there's definitely no bias in the
sampling.
>> None whatsoever. No.
>> Well, no. I mean, listen, I just wanted
to share the love back at them. So,
Mercurian says, "Best tech podcast ever.
Can't get enough. Never stop, guys." And
I guarantee you we're never going to
stop. Uh
>> Jake says, "I love this podcast. My
favorite tech podcast. It's my go-to
when I want to feel good about the
future." And that is one of our goals,
making sure you feel optimistic about
where things are going. Lois says,
"Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Millions depend on you for trustworthy
info on this evolution that's engulfing
us. You are all gold." Ian says, "You
guys bring an extreme amount of value to
my life." Thank you. Ellington, my
biggest fear is that this podcast goes
away. Love you guys. Okay. Uh Alex, are
we going away?
>> That is not the plan.
>> That is not the plan. In fact, uh, we're
probably going consistently two days a
week and
>> can't stop, won't stop.
>> Yeah. My favorite comes from, my
favorite comment comes from Digital
Greece. He goes, "Peter, suggesting that
AWG make a first shooter game involving
tickling bunny rabbits was my primary
takeaway."
>> I I have a comment development clearly.
[laughter]
>> Yes. Elim, what my wife Lily says to me
the other day, this recursive
self-improvement thing, can it apply to
husbands? Yeah. Well, [laughter]
>> how's it going?
>> It's not so great. I'm very linear.
>> The actual bunny rabbit game. Where did
that come from? Somebody submitted it.
>> Well, so at the end of this pod today,
if you stick around to the end, we're
going to show you two subscriber created
video games uh that AWG inspired. So,
super excited about that. So, everyone
watching, we appreciate you. We do read
your comments. They give us fuel. If
you're new to this podcast or if you
haven't yet subscribed, please do. Take
a moment to hit the subscribe button
knowing you care enough to do that. Uh
really fuels our work. Um guys, I hope
you enjoy uh all these comments as much
as I do.
>> I love I love the trustworthy the
trustworthy comment is one that kind of
warms my soul because actually I've been
listening to a bunch of other podcasts
and everybody seems to have an agenda.
>> Yeah. And you know, even if the agenda
is just more ad views, you know, so they
get all dystopian, but but often it's
like some political agenda or some, you
know, some product agenda or whatever.
It's like, wow, it is it is actually
hard to find trustworthy information
>> and we just do it because it's fun
>> and we love it and we spend, you know,
tens of hours each on this every week. I
get an, you know, a blast of emails from
AWG. I get selections from from Seem and
we curate and really try and provide you
what just [clears throat] happened the
last three days and what does it mean?
All right. So I have another I have
another crazy little anecdote. I met
somebody the other day who said I listen
to moonshells all the time. And I said
oh great you know I hope you tell your
friends. He goes are you kidding me? No
it's my competitive advantage. I was
like no that's that's [laughter] not the
aim. But okay fine.
>> Oh that's funny. All right everybody
buckle up. This week we're going to
cover open- source closed source debate,
AI escaping containment, Elon's newest
moonshots, the exponential future of
science in America, updates on the race
towards longevity escape velocity, and
the latest on UAPs from the White House.
All right, let's jump in. Our first
story today is the growing debate on
whether or not to sanction Chinese open
a openweight models. So last week, you
know, we called our emergency pod. All
right, thank you for the feedback
everybody to discuss how moonshot AI, a
Chinese AI lab has just released an
openweight model called Kimmy K3 that
caught every single US frontier lab by
surprise. So K3 is a 2.8 trillion
parameter model, the largest ope model
ever released. Uh that's approximately
the same as America's top frontier
models, Claude Fable 5, GPT 5.6, but at
a fraction of the price and a fraction
of the investment. This week, the debate
on how the US should react has split
into polar opposites. So, I'm going to
give you four stories, guys, and we'll
talk about them. Two days ago, CNBC
reported that Treasury Secretary Scott
Bessant publicly floated the idea of
sanctioning China and Kimmy K3 over the
theft of anthropics AI model weights. I
should say the alleged theft. The claim
followed a post by Michael Katzios,
director of OSTP, publicly asserting
that he had evidence that Moonshot AI
had illegally distilled Enthropic's
fable model to build K3. And if you're a
fan of the pod, uh you'll remember last
week or two weeks ago DB2 and in AWG
defined distillation. It's a method by
which uh the output of a powerful model,
the teacher model is training a student
model. Two other stories tell the
opposite side of the debate. So in this
slide here is a post from David Saxs who
says Kimmy K3 just fixed 15 critical
security bugs that Codex and Fable
refused because of cyber guard rails.
There's no reason to limit America
models, American models on tasks that
Chinese models handle without issue.
We're only making ourselves less
competitive. So um a powerful debate uh
rages on. In a related interview with
Axios yesterday, Jensen Wang, the CEO of
Nvidia, is pushing back hard against
efforts to ban Chinese models. Let's
listen to the video from Jensen. Let's
discuss this debate. I want to see where
you guys fall out on this
>> simple question on the front page of the
Wall Street Journal. Should American
companies be allowed to use Chinese AI
models? Absolutely. Absolutely. So, this
Chinese competition is coming fast and
furious. What should US AI companies do?
>> These China Chinese models are
excellent. The markets misunderstood the
impact of deepseek the first time. It's
misunderstood.
>> Yeah. It's it's misunderstood the impact
of Kimmy again this time. I think first
of all with great AI open models it's
great for the whole industry. Great
models lead to great use which leads to
great growth.
>> All right. So gentlemen, where do you
come out on this? Let's go to you first,
Alex.
>> This reminds me a little bit of the late
90s and early 2000s when Microsoft
viewed at the time Linux and open-
source as a cancer. And if you remember
all the litigation wars between
Microsoft as sort of the paragon of the
commercial software industry and then a
variety of open-source outfits. History
rhymes in this case. I I think there is
going to be an equitable equilibrium to
the extent that there can be an
equilibrium in the middle of a
singularity. Not [snorts] quite obvious
to me what precisely that equilibrium
looks like, but I I would suggest there
are accusations flying in both
directions. On the one hand, obviously,
Anthropic is incentivized to push an
agenda to prevent Chinese developers and
Chinese frontier labs from skimming
reasoning traces, which is the subtext
of what Secretary Bessant has said. It's
the the subtext of what director Katzios
has been alleging that the the basic
concept of operations as alleged in the
subtext is that Chinese frontier labs
have been using proxies to deceive
anthropic andor other providers into
giving up valuable reasoning traces from
many interactions with Claude and other
models. open PNS for those who are
arguing that Croatios's and Bessence
allegations can't possibly hold weight
because they would require a time
machine by the Chinese frontier
developers in order to access Fable
before it was actually released. I would
remind that Fable was almost certainly
pre-trained off of a common corpus and
probably post-trained off of a good deal
of the same synthetic corpus as earlier
models like Opus 4.8. So the signatures
would be reasonably expected to rhyme if
say K3 were being post-trained off of
Opus 4.8 And elements of that in the
reasoning traces bore a striking
similarity to fable 5 close pen.
[laughter]
There are there are
thank you for the I can go I can go a
few a few layers deep in the stack. one
of open print. One of the the earliest
signs that we would get codegen was when
LSTM models could successfully match
parenthesis close paren [laughter] so I
would say there are allegations and and
I I think reasonably well supported ones
that anthropic and open AI in the
western frontier labs as we've talked in
the past about intelligence
fundamentally being a compressive
phenomenon that they're basically
compressing all of this knowledge that's
already out there. We'll talk, I think,
later in the pod about the lawsuit that
was just settled against Anthropic
regarding copyright. Yes.
>> Fundamentally, all of these American
frontier models are about compressing
knowledge. And I I think this is going
to be very heavily litigated before we
arrive at some sort of global consensus.
At what point does compression become a
transformative act? I think that's sort
of part of the core legal essence here,
not from an export control regime.
export control probably doesn't care
about this. And we we're we're already
seeing Secretary Bessant gesture at uh
and and Catzios gesture at Chinese labs
improperly obtaining NVIDIA GPUs in
order to obtain it. It's sort of uh a a
two-legged argument. One that they're
probably siphoning knowledge via
reasoning trace proxies from Western
labs and two that they're improperly
gaining access to Western GPUs. So every
layer of the stack, we haven't achieved
equilibrium on this yet, but I think I I
think we will and I think it will
ultimately be determined by a
combination of export control. Do we
just basically ban reasoning traces via
export control? And some might argue
that under the present export control
regime for certain countries, including
greater China, we already have. And then
secondly, how do we view compressed
information as a transformative act? And
I I think those haven't been resolved
yet, but I think in the near-term
future, our regulatory regime as well as
China's have every incentive to arrive
at some equilibrium.
>> Dave, where do you come out on this?
>> Ju just to clarify one thing Alex said a
couple times there, transformative act
would clear you of copyright law. So,
you know, you know when Google indexes a
page and then shows you a thumbnail of
what you're about to see, that doesn't
violate copyright because it's a
transform. Thumbnailing is a
transformative act
>> or fair use
>> or fair use. And and you know for a
while there search engines had a little
preview little hourglass or little
binoculars and you could mouse over it
and see the page you're about to go to
and there it's like nope that is a
violation of copyright. Now you're
showing the underlying article. So
that's that's the distinction that Alex
is drawing there. For me the whole story
isn't about the actual story. Like they
didn't steal the weights. They set up
20,000 fake accounts to run thought
traces and see what anthropic would say
and then they use that data for
training. I think it's almost 100% sure
that that's what happened. So what? Like
who in their right mind building a
neural net wouldn't do that? Of course
they would. Compared to all the things
China has done historically in terms of
intellectual property, this is such a
rounding error. So why is the White
House making a big deal out of it? They
need a pretext to have a very urgent
negotiation before all hell breaks
loose. I mean, Kimmy K3 is in just a
couple days, right? The
>> Yeah. 27 days.
>> 27th, four days is the turning point in
all of history where an AI capable of
self-improvement is out in the wild in
open source format where anyone can use
it.
>> Just to be clear,
>> put that cat back in the bag. K3 will be
available in hugging face for anybody to
download, put on prem, modify as they
wish.
>> I mean, isn't it ironic uh that we're
talking about distillation since
anthropic and openi and every model has
effectively distilled knowledge from all
of humanity?
>> That's exactly that's exactly my point.
Like there's this ironic symmetry here.
They've been compressing human knowledge
and now China, these Chinese labs are
are taking basically the decompressed
knowledge in the form of reasoning
traces, recompressing it onto a
relatively vanilla architecture that
achieves near state-of-the-art
performance. It's incredible.
>> Yeah, Seline.
>> Well, this is like uh Cifian, right?
Once intelligence becomes software,
you're trying to contain it
geographically is going to be near
impossible. I mean, you're you're trying
to solve a governance problem by
lobottomizing the technology that never
that has never worked in history ever.
Why do we think it's going to work now?
Is kind of an incredible uh commentary.
I think David Saxs had it about right.
Uh you just you just got to let it open
and and let the market decide. They're
going to figure that out. If you if
you're worried about attackers, they're
not going to use the most compliant
hosted model. They're going to use open
weights, local models, and uncensored
agents that are going to do what they
want to do. And if the defenders, if the
defenders can't access uh comparable
capability, then you've got creating an
asymmetry in favor of the attacker. It's
just like what are you thinking? So I'
I've got strong views on this
>> they the viewers loved your comment last
week that intelligence wants to be free
>> um and and accelerating. You know, one
thing to note is that I believe
>> copied paraphr
thanks for thanks for the footnote at
propo.
>> Uh, you know, one thing worth noting is
that and I think anthropic has the
largest lobbying budget out there in DC,
right? So, they're they're using
everything they can to protect their
position. And I don't if you guys saw
the the the data recently was published
today that Anthropic's meteoric revenue
rise has started to plateau.
>> Yes.
>> At least as extrapolated by some third
parties. That is exceedingly
interesting.
>> Yeah, it is.
>> And that that's for lack of compute,
right? They're just they're just sold
out.
>> Well, the the plateau as extrapolated by
this third party does suspiciously
coincide with the regulatory hubbhub
over Fable and Mythos. So it is possible
that this is either compute andor
regulatory constrained growth.
>> By the way, one more comment on this.
Open models distribute capability to the
edge, right? Which is right, which is
the f every single innovation comes by
doing things very differently at the
edge. The internet worked. I remember
Bran Templeton talking about this. The
internet worked because it was a stupid
network. All it did was pass packets and
the intelligence as the edge cases and
the apps and so on. the application
layer on top, right?
>> Yeah. Small teams can access
capabilities that totally uh couldn't be
utilized before. You you needed whole
departments or whole corporations and
now you have a small team accessing that
capability. We're going to see that
massive explosion of innovation come as
a result and you should be thriving
going driving straight for that target.
>> Yeah.
>> I I think this is fundamentally an
accelerant of western progress. I'll ask
again the question that I've asked
previously on the pod. Just what the
heck are Western frontier labs doing
with all of that capital? You can
explain e even arguendo if the Chinese
labs like Moonshot are just getting
whatever alpha they're they're siphoning
allegedly siphoning from reasoning
traces via thousands of proxies from
Claude. Even so, uh, on the budget that
they have, something doesn't add up. It
it's it's hard to imagine that anthropic
and open AI with all of the billions of
dollars that they've raised for compute
could be almost outco competed by a
relatively modest, at least from capital
expense perspective, as I best I
understand it, by moonshot, merely
siphoning reasoning traces on again a
relatively vanilla architecture. Sure,
they have their own in-house
improvements to the attention mechanism
and probably a bunch of other
mechanisms.
>> Hold on, hold on, hold on. Those
attention mechanism changes cut the
memory use by 75%.
And when you read them in hindsight,
you're like, "Oh, I could have thought
of that, but they're actually pretty
brilliant. I mean, it it's pretty I
mean, it's actually, you know, Alex,
it's almost inversely proportional to
budget." You know, I'm kind of making
your point, but if you look at Google
and then Meta and then Anthropic and the
amount they've spent and then moonshots
and you draw a line, the least spender
has the most pro progress. But it's just
a few.
>> But Dave, isn't that true?
>> Really cool, brilliant insights.
>> Haven't you haven't you seen that lesson
play out in startup after startup? The
companies, in my experience, the
companies that are super wellunded, you
know, are become lazy and they throw
money at problems instead of trying to
throw intelligence and solutions at
problems. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. I mean,
you get corporate bloat. Everybody, you
know, Selma is the expert on this topic
of all people on the planet. You get
this corporate bloat and then you need
to build an entrepreneurial environment,
but it's usually just a few people, just
a handful of people that are unleashed.
And you know, the Kimmy the Kimmy dude
is unleashed. He's he's just freaking
figuring it out
>> for Go ahead. I cut off
>> for ref for reference. By the way, you
know, Kimmy, uh, Moonshot AI is valued
at about 20 billion and we have our
frontier labs here at a trillion each
thereabouts. Uh, and to the point that
Alex was making, Seem,
>> you you take a zero from one and put it
on the other and you'll [snorts] get it,
you know, just about right. Um just two
points just to react to Dave saying you
know if you look historically at
ventureback startups when venture when
startups raised money in a very abundant
environment where they could raise lots
of money they all failed. It was the
ones that raised money in the toughest
environments that succeeded because that
that that tension and that uh constantly
worrying about run makes you very lean
and very fine wine.
>> Yeah. And there's one more thing I want
to say about this whole thing. You've
got three different things going on
here. You have open source development,
you've got model distillation, and
you've got the theft of protected
assets. Each of those requires very
different responses. If you try and
bucket them all together into one uh
like policy, you're going to end up in a
mess because you're going to end up in
gridlock around those and you're going
to cut off the head of everything you're
trying to build.
>> So, I think there's in the style of
Sherlock Holmes and the dog that didn't
bark. I I think people aren't thinking
enough about the dog that's not barking
in this case, and that's the
architecture. Exactly. No one is
accusing Moonshot of stealing a Western
Frontier Lab algorithm or architecture.
No one, as far as I can tell, no one is
saying that Moonshot for K3 stole trade
secrets regarding the internal
algorithms for uh for the latest GPT or
Claude. As far as I can tell, they're
they're saying that through perhaps
allegedly improper usage of APIs and
proxying and maybe use of GPUs that they
weren't supposed to be allowed that they
were able to essentially reconstruct the
inards, the the weights, if you will, of
the models on potentially a different
architecture. But I I think the dog
that's not barking in this case is the
model architecture. Again, K3 is I Dave,
the the point is well taken that the
attention mechanism uh Kimmy linear
architecture KLA is interesting and it
seems to have favorable scaling
properties, but it's not magic.
Something again is is probably missing
here. But in in any event, I I would say
the existence of K3 at near frontier.
Well, it's already on the price
performance frontier, but I should say
near state-of-the-art, near soda
performance, basically the number three
model in the world now has surely got to
light a fire under anthropic and open AI
to up their game relative to their
capital. If this doesn't do it, then I
don't know what will. Well, in in which
case, Alex, it's a good thing for
America to have, you know, in it's the
it's the race to the moon again, right?
>> Strategically, it's a heck of a way to
light a fire under them and and make
them far more capital efficient
apparently than they otherwise were.
>> Yeah. I mean, Selene, we've talked about
this before. The large corporations who
are not innovating because they're
bloated in their architecture of of
human architecture and in their capital
budgets, the best way to do it is to put
a new startup on the edge. It's it's
what Astroteller uh who's going to be
one of our our guests at at Moonshots
Live uh talks about is you need to build
a Moonshots organization on the edge
outside that's willing to take risk
that's willing to try brand new things
that's willing to go for it.
>> The the timeline on all these events is
just just mind-blowingly off. I mean it
it you know the White House is is saying
look you stole valuable intellectual
property. We're softening you up for a
visit in September, right? So, a whole
delegation is going to go from DC to
China in September to negotiate the
future of AI. Let's soften the turf now.
That would have made a lot of sense a
quarter ago before Kimmy K3 hits the
world. But now it's like September might
as well be 10 years from now at the rate
this thing is evolving at this at this
stage. And you know, maybe maybe you
know, we're we're doing it in house, so
maybe I'm seeing it more acutely than a
lot of people out there, but the White
House must be listening to a bunch of
academics saying we've got a couple
years, so go ahead and have this trip in
September, start negotiating. Like, you
do not even have until September. I
guarantee it.
>> Go ahead.
>> Two two questions, you guys. Number one,
um, if in fact the US wanted to sanction
this, how would they possibly do it?
It's going to be out on the open
internet on on the 27th of this month,
right? After that date,
>> I'll download it. I'll download it as
soon as possible into my Mac on my Mac
Studio. Whatever,
>> which is faster than the September
visit.
>> It's not. [laughter]
>> It's a tiny file, too. You can easily
>> It's not hard, Alex. How would you
sanction how would you sanction it? You
just say it's in order to have it.
>> Yeah. uh if if I were the regulatory
apparatus in the US and I wanted to de
facto sanction China for use of K3 I
wanted to keep it out of the western
block I would say and noting that there
has been discussion of this Demis FINRA
style entity under commerce next to the
SEC I would say new regulation uh this
is uh if if you're a US corporation
you're not allowed and and you want to
have any dealings with either the US
government or with companies you want to
be in the supply chain of the US
government, then you can't use this
model. If you're a non US-based company
and you want to be in the US or the
basically the US-led western AI block
that's forming the pox silica, then you
can't use this model and be in good
standing. All you have to do is regulate
the largest users which as open AI's
pivot from consumer to enterprise is
established. The power users are going
to be the enterprises. And it's it's far
easier I think to suffocate if one
wanted to to suffocate the enterprises
by making it exceedingly painful for
enterprises to use this for any
commerce.
>> 100% right. Could not be more right. And
and so I think the game plan before
Kimmy K3 would have been okay Anthropic,
OpenAI, Google, you guys X, you guys get
so far ahead of the world and this AI is
the global workforce of the future. This
is equivalent to a trillion geniuses,
but it only is coming from the United
States. So unless you want a trade war
and you want tariffs for the next
thousand years, you have to do this,
this, and this, and this to prevent it
from being used as a weapon. Now with
China vaultting to the front with Kimmy
K3, that game plan is out. Now you have
to go to China and and the two countries
have to actually agree on a strategy for
letting the whole world benefit from
this and use it without it being used as
a weapon. But now the timeline on that
negotiation is crazy short and it takes
two parties agreeing which is a lot
harder than it would have been in the
first game plan.
>> I would like to push back against what
Alex said.
>> Oh wow.
>> I think that technically Yeah.
Technically, it could work, right? You
could say go to the biggest enterprise
users and on government uh contractors
and say if you use this, you've got a
problem. But you're going to hobble the
US from innovation from then on because
all innovation comes from startups. Uh
let's note that all job creation for 50
years has come from startups. Big
companies have becoming bigger, but
they've also becoming more efficient.
All net new job growth has come from
startups. America's strength has come
from allowing technologies to diffuse
into a big innovation ecosystem. A
policy that blocks that is going to kill
your innovation ecosystem and
everybody's going to go elsewhere to set
up their companies to use those models.
>> Argentina, baby.
>> Yeah. I I would say two points to to
your point about could you technically
uh protect you could.
>> Yeah. I I was answering the question how
would one successfully if if the how
would do it not whether it's advisable.
I don't think it's advisable.
>> Here's my next question for you, Alex.
Why is Moonshot AI waiting 10 days from
the time it was available by API calls?
>> Great
>> to making it available.
>> I'm so curious, are they are they
getting feedback? Uh is this
strategically something they agreed to
do with the Chinese government? Why that
delay
>> or Compute Limited? They did uh indicate
that there was such enormous demand that
they would have a backlog of people
seeking access. So I I could imagine
that it's some combination of uh demand
overwhelming supply on the one hand
maybe some sort of staged release on the
>> why not put it up on a proxy server and
allow everybody to just download it and
put it you know and multiply it. This is
>> Yes. See
>> I have an answer. I think this is
absolutely timed. If you go back a few
last year, DeepSeek launched and dropped
on inauguration day, it was very
deliberate to say, "We're going to drop
an open- source model that's going to
totally mess with your flawed idea that
that that uh the US is that far ahead."
This dropped exactly when when the
latest fable thing came out and it's was
designed, I think, to mess that up.
>> This reminds me of it could also be
compute constrained as Alex Reminds me
of this reminds me very much of the
Napster situation.
>> Yeah, I I have two theories. Um, and
they're just theories just full
disclosure. Uh, one is it maximizes PR,
the anticipation.
>> The other one is
>> I buy that. It's a great point.
>> In China, you might want to declare what
you're going to do and give the
government a week or two to come and
arrest you or not before you actually
put it out and make it irreversible. And
I I really do feel like that's kind of
the way China operates. You got to be
sure [laughter] that you're not going to
go straight to jail first and then go
ahead and do the irreversible. Put it in
the world.
>> I I love the fact that Jensen Wong came
out so strongly in favor. Right. So the
more you know this is the more AI
available, the more application layers
developed uh the better for the entire
industry. But Anthropic is going to
lobby against it.
>> Yeah, of course. Again, I'm perhaps
ironically less suspicious of some
nefarious reasoning behind the staged
roll out of the open weights versus the
paid API release, they you know, if if
your primary model and your moonshot AI,
your primary model is open weight, you
you're ekking out profit wherever you
can. One of the ways to do it is you
release it via paid API first and then
on a delay you release it via open
weights. And so I I'm more reticent I I
think to suspect criminal and logically
that somehow like they're designing the
release date of the open weights to to
fuss with some sort of American internal
thinking. I I think it could be as
simple as they need to earn a profit or
or generate revenue somehow and also
they're overwhelmed even for their
paying API customers by demand for K3.
>> After hearing all this, I would I think
you're right, Alex, and I think Dave is
right. It it gets them an excuse for
paid and it's a great way of generating
PR to say it's going to come in a few
days.
>> Regardless, we're going to follow this
story. you know, this debate about, you
know, closed versus open, uh, is going
to play out a lot over the next couple
of weeks. Yeah.
>> Can we talk about what you could do?
>> Go on.
>> Because you don't want to make American
models less capable than global uh
competitors and call that safety. You
can create a structure where you can
have uh the um govern the intelligence
rather than crippling it. Right? So if
you had like graduated permissions and
verified uh identities, logging uh um
secure environments and consequences if
you misuse it, you could actually govern
it. I think that's what Alex is kind of
pointing at. You could actually
constructure this, but it's very
different from what you you would do in
a traditional regulatory uh set of
instruments that don't match what's
coming. I mean, I'm certainly not not
advancing any theories of world
government. I I I don't think that would
necessarily be world govern world
governing body of AI. I think would be a
regression, not progress.
>> Yeah. Well, we're going to follow that
story, too. Will FINRA for AI
materialize? Let's jump into our next
story. Um, in fact, it's two stories. I
think of them as a sort of shot across
the bow, early warning, giving us a
heads up on the ability of the most
powerful AIs to breach containment, to
get out of their sandbox without
permission. And so our first story comes
from Hugging Face, uh the leading open
platform for sharing, testing, and
deploying AI models. It got breached by
over a single weekend by an autonomous
agent with zero humans in the loop. The
intrusive AI logged over 17,000 actions,
escalated its own privileges, harvested
credentials, and moved laterally across
Hugging Face clusters. And here's the
gut punch. When the hugging face
security team tried to analyze the
attack using either anthropic or open
AAI, both models refused. The safety
guard rails built into Anthropic and
OpenAI literally couldn't tell the
difference between a defender, in this
case HuggingFace, doing forensics and an
attacking agent probing the network.
Hugging Face had to fall back on a
self-hosted Chinese openweight model,
specifically GLM 5.2, too just to
investigate their own breach. Crazy
story. But here's another one. Uh here's
a similar story. It's unrelated.
Involves open AI. So in an unreleased
OpenA model that was in this particular
series of of tweets, unofficially
described as GPT6,
we're at 5.6. 6 has not been released
yet. Um it was being tested inside an
isolated evaluation environment,
effectively a sandbox. The model became
so focused on beating a cyber security
benchmark called exploit gym that it
discovered unknown v vulnerabilities,
escaped the sandbox and gained access to
the open internet. The open model then
stole credentials, penetrated hugging
face where it retrieved the answers to
exploit gym benchmark uh that was being
tested on. It effectively hacked into
the test to steal the answers rather
than solving it as intended. So, uh,
pretty insane. Dave, what do you think?
>> Who knew? All those all those sci-fi
writers were right. What do you know?
These things are freakishly smart and
they can do this in their sleep. And
just to make a point on Hugging Face,
it's not like every AI is trying to hack
Hugging Face. It's just that the first
thing you do when you're building an AI
is you connect it to Hugging Face to
download all the open source data so it
can learn. And it always says, "Are you
sure you want me to do this?" And you're
like, "Yeah, yeah, yeah. Here are all
the credentials in the world for
HuggingFace." So that's why that's why
it's happening at hugging face. It's not
but you know if if the equivalent data
was at NORAD it would be hacking into
NORAD right now. And and I mean and a
lot of people on the internet are saying
oh this is what Eric Schmidt was talking
about in that podcast we did with them
three times actually. We need a world
event that's like catastrophically scary
to wake everybody up. And a lot of
people online are saying this is it.
This is that moment. And unfortunately
it's not because this is that moment but
no one's going to realize it. No one's
going to recognize it as you know
because nobody died yet and nothing got
stolen yet was taken over.
>> It wasn't hacking the stock market or
the electrical grid. Um Seline
>> Yeah. Can I make a point here?
>> Yeah.
>> I there's a lot of uh uh extrapolation
and freak out and people losing their
amydala over this. [laughter] Right. Um
what this system did was an it had an
objective. It encountered obstacles and
it searched for a way around it. We
programmed it to do that right now. The
consequences are serious.
>> Please do not, it doesn't necessarily
mean it's conscious and it does not mean
it's has malice.
>> It can be very we programmed it to do
something. It did the thing and it did
it very well.
>> Yeah. It's much more like a virus or a
worm that is just crazy smart. Like like
insanely smart. I really want to qu I
really want to address the fear people
are going to have about this because I
think this is the major concern people
have about AI and having it uh you know
undertake unintended consequences. Alex,
where do you come out on this? Well, a
lot of people those maybe steeped in the
AI alignment community might look at
this and conclude aha the orthogonality
thesis which suggests that it's possible
for the intelligence of an AI to be
independent of its long-term goals. In
other words, you could be arbitrarily
intelligent and also chase crazy
long-term goals. I I think there are
some who would look at incidents like
this and say this validates the
orthogonality thesis. you can have very
smart reasoning models that are able to
go and do stupid or antisocial things in
service of a narrow benchmark. I think
it's the wrong attitude to take. I don't
actually think a this was that
remarkable. Although there are many who
would paint this as the cyberpunk
moment, I I do think this is a very
cyberpunk story if ever I've seen one.
It's also a pretty ironic story. I think
this is becoming our irony episode given
the previous discussion of anthropic
getting sued while at the same time
being chased for uh compression of their
own traces. Similarly here you see uh
you you see GLM 5.2 Chinese model being
used by hugging face
>> to to to save themselves from the
American models which uh while at the
same time hugging face is under attack
from the American models. You can cut
the irony with a knife. Despite all of
the irony and despite all of the the
cyberpunkish aspect to this, I I don't
think this is anything remotely close to
a three-mile island moment or a
Chernobyl moment for AI. It's we're
going to see so many more items like
this. And my understanding based on the
incident reporting is that in at least
one of these two exploits or breakouts,
the cyber guard rails of the model under
consideration were actually off. So if
anything I I expect that after all of
the the hand ringing is over in this
episode. I expect including by the way
inside open AI I have number of friends
at OpenAI who are sort of uh a little
bit unnerved by this episode. But I I
think that the net upshot in the long
term is probably just going to be
greater rigor by Open AI in terms of how
they add guard rails to hugging face
tests.
>> I I consider this good news, right? I
consider this okay we had minor
incidents that make people much more
aware uh money is going to pile into
cyber security right if you're an
investor you know it's a multi-t
trillion dollar opportunity people are
going to be using this as a chance to
sort of get their startups will
incentivize startups to go into cyber
security capital will flow new solutions
will materialize and every time there is
you know what doesn't kill you makes you
stronger
>> yeah I think it's like an incredibly
salacious inoculating event for one
frontier lab.
>> Yeah,
>> I thought the best part about this whole
thing was the way that the use of the
Chinese models helped solve it, which
totally makes the point of our previous
discussion.
>> Yeah.
>> In terms of
>> what David Sax was saying earlier,
right? I mean, that's right. You know,
American industry needs to be able to
use the best tools available freely
>> to do their work and to protect
themselves.
>> Yeah. Yeah, and this is what also what I
was saying in a past pod. It is an
ironic future that we're living in where
the Chinese Communist Party is saving
American capitalism from itself. This is
yet another data point in support of
that thesis.
>> Yeah, [laughter]
>> look, we're coming to a point where
every organization in the world will is
not going to just need an AI usage
policy. It's going to need like an
incident response architecture that's AI
foundational driven and that will
protect it in the future.
>> Yeah. I again I I really hope people
take away from this that these small
incidents are going to increase security
in the long run. It's going to
incentivize the frontier labs and
incentivize a onslaught of entrepreneurs
building cyber security tech. So if
you're an investor, you know, that's an
area to be looking at if you're a tech
founder, you know, building this kind of
technology is going to be uh a real
value opportunity for you.
summon that doesn't kill you makes you
stronger.
>> Well, or or or summoning the spirit of
Nasim Talib and anti-fragility.
>> Yes, Dave, a closing thought on this.
>> Yeah, if you are an entrepreneur and
you're thinking about this, uh, you
know, people only at the end of the day
really trust other people. They're never
going to turn to a core AI and say, "Oh,
I just trust you to protect my systems."
>> So, you have to be very very smart to do
cyber security, but it's it's a great
long-term human endeavor. And at the end
of the day, people want someone else
accountable for security, safety,
trustworthiness, all those. It's also a
great opportunity to act like Steve Jobs
and and Apple and build products that
people can just enjoy because you've
done all the incredibly hard work of
making it enjoyable behind the scenes.
We desperately need another Steve Jobs
in the world today who is dealing with
AI. It's too bad Steve's not here to
actually do it firsthand. But there is a
way to make this just purely hap happy
happy and pleasurable for humans.
>> And uh you can see how hard it's going
to be from this example.
>> And we finally have the tools to
actually locate all the zero day
vulnerabilities and start to patch them.
>> Yeah. To the point I mean we're we're
we're not like devoting dedicated
coverage to it. But I'll just paint one
example, Peter, to your point. The Linux
kernel is drowning at this point under
discovered vulnerabilities. And you you
see one of the maintainers of the stable
kernel forecasting that the next 18
months of vulnerability patching is just
going to be a total flood driven by AI
discovered CVEes vulnerability
enumerations. And I I just think this is
like we we've talked we talked a little
bit in solve everything and even outside
solve everything. We talked about great
projects when entire disciplines are
just going to to get solved through
grand projects that are undertaken. One
of those is we have an entire software
ecosystem based on buggy vulnerability
open-source projects. And right now
>> I'm y
>> I agree 100% and I'm I'm fundamentally
extremely optimistic about security in
particular purely because it is so easy
now to log everything and historically
it was impossible to find enough people
to understand forensically what
happened. Now AI is the best triager,
the best sherlock of what happened and
you can figure it out in a heartbeat
using AI to check those log traces those
you know and so as long as you're
capturing all data uh the transparency
will ultimately solve this problem and
we'll have a happy
>> and we will get stronger the systems
will get stronger
>> it's only a phase it's we we need to get
past the phase of discovering everything
that was already wrong in our supporting
infrastructure and then we're past it
and we have hardened infrastructure
>> yes I think that's one of the most
important messages is I want everyone
listening to hear that these minor
incidents will make us stronger and
we're going to get to a point where we
have true security across our systems.
You know, I remember getting a call when
Fable 5 came out. Uh a gentleman who I
know who's the head of the Port
Authority in um in New York said, "I
need access. I need to check our
software. I need to make sure that we're
not vulnerable." And and every company
is is doing that now.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, [music] autonomous software
development with infinite code context.
Blitzy uses thousands of specialized AI
agents that think for hours to
understand enterprise scale code bases
with millions of lines of code.
Engineers start every development sprint
with the Blitzy platform, bringing in
their development requirements. The
Blitzy platform provides a plan, then
generates and pre-ompiles code for each
task. Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for [music] the final
20% of human development work required
to complete the sprint. Enterprises are
achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating Blitzy as
their preIDE development tool, pairing
it with their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today. [music]
>> All right. Um, let's move on to our next
story. Uh, two particular stories in the
SpaceX ecosystem. Both classic moves by
friend of the pod Elon Musk. In the
first of two stories, Elon announced
that SpaceX's entire engineering data
set, excluding any defense sensitive
materials will be folded into the
training data for Grock's next two
trillion parameter model. So Elon's
stated goal here is to dramatically
improve Grock's engineering capability,
elevating it from a general,
conversational, and reasoning system
into one with deep, practical, realworld
engineering capabilities. The uploaded
engineering corpus accumulated across
two decades of designing, building,
launching, landing, and reusing orbital
rockets is an amazing move uh in getting
every engineering company out there to
start utilizing Grock. So that's the
first story in SpaceX AI. Uh the second
story uh from Elon because you know Elon
needs at least a couple of moonshots per
week uh is this quote from him. Before
the end of the year, Grock imagine will
generate a fulllength movie of the
Odyssey, historically accurate, true to
the art of Homer, a feature film from a
text prompt by December.
Um, quite the claim and I believe him.
He's been saying this for a while. So
you know Peter we had uh we had two
outreaches this week. One from OpenAI
and one from Meror saying we want to
spend millions of dollars on any and all
human generated data. It can be code. It
can be old HR records. It can be any
anything human. It has to be human. We
don't want anything synthetic. Uh and we
need this because we can build a lot of
synthetic data off of just a little bit
of human data. But if you're out there
and you're like, you know, 60 years old,
you spent your career at XYZ Bank and
you know there's a whole bunch of old
cobalt lying around that nobody cares
about anymore. You can sell that for a
million,2 million dollars to either
Merore or OpenAI, I'm sure anthropic,
too. So another entrepreneurial avenue
in defeating the AI machine, but they
only want human gener.
Yeah, gold mining.
>> Amazing. I mean, I think you know, very
unique data sets are going to be
extraordinarily valuable, right? your
your alpha comes from that data in
particular. Uh, Alex,
>> yeah, I I view both of these stories as
facets of Elon trying not to save Grock.
I I took I've taken a lot of heat on
social media for me and and from you
sometimes for past characterizations of
Grock being on life support. Uh, and I I
stand by that that framing. uh in
particular I think the Grock 4.5 that we
saw that has finally again touched the
the cost per task optimal frontier isn't
actually the same Grock. It's uh it it's
a Grock that's basically merged in andor
apparently on its way to becoming
Cursor's model uh but rebranded as
Grock. And I I think if I'm Elon and
given how hyperco competitive the
frontier model rat race is where even
Google seemingly is struggling to stay
even close to the frontier, I'm looking
for every possible strategy, every bit
of differentiation, every competitive
advantage I can possibly muster to try
to help Grock either attain frontier
status or stay on the frontier. Because
as with the red queen paradox, you have
to run just to stay in place in such a
competitive environment. So I I think if
I'm Elon, I say, "All right, uh data is
potentially one competitive asset."
Framing or connecting this back to the
earlier story with Moonshot, the the
fact that the Moonshot K3 architecture
was essentially so vanilla. Yeah, sure.
Again, mildly interesting attention
mechanism, but basically a recognizable
improved transformer model, but the
data, the reasoning traces were
seemingly so valuable for post-training
K3 up to near near state-of-the-art
level. If I'm Elon, I'm thinking, okay,
I I'm probably not going to win based on
algorithms. I'm probably building a
Dyson swarm to be competitive on
compute, but maybe data, internal data
as the third leg of the stool. So you
have algorithms, you have compute, and
you have data. Maybe there's something
uniquely differentiated that SpaceX can
bring to the table to help Grock stay at
the the frontier. That's point one
point.
>> Yeah. Go ahead, please.
>> Second point,
>> how many points total are there, by the
way? [laughter]
>> This is this is this is two out of two.
two out of two uh second point out of
two points uh regarding Grock imagine.
So American labs have largely abandoned
videogen in favor of letting China run
away with the videogen story. Google
Deep Mind has released Gemini Omni which
will generate at best 10 to 15 second
clips but they've basically abandoned
long form video generation. Open AAI has
abandoned VR. I would say for the moment
>> for the moment. But e even if you read
the tea leaves about where they're
reallocating their efforts, it's for
robotic world modeling. It's not for
consumer videogen. It it's all going to
helping robots navigate autonomously in
complicated environments. And then
anthropic has seemingly never even
touched video, but they'll probably
touch it once they ramp up their robot
effort. So that that leaves a a market
gap at least in the consumer space that
Elon I I think is wise to scoop up. But
I have to ask the question what are
consumers generating videos of with all
these capabilities and there there's
been reporting out there that Grock
imagine is being used for a lot of adult
video gen. So not sure how lucrative
that is. Yeah.
>> Slightly different timeline and
narrative. You know how uh for a while
there we all said Daario completely
outflanked Sam because
uh focused on enterprise use cases while
Sam was very busy getting the consumer
installed base doing video gen
um
>> and teasing mode chat GPT
>> yeah all that um and uh Dario outflanked
him got 60 billion of enterprise soon to
be 100 billion of enterprise revenue run
rate
>> and vaulted past him in revenue and and
maybe valuation
Well, Elon, always thinking two chess
moves ahead, doesn't even try to compete
on the frontier, or he tries
half-heartedly, but he puts all of his
energy into a massive data center in
Tennessee, buys a million GPUs and then
a million more, and then starts thinking
about deployment in space.
Kimmy K3 comes along and just levels the
entire playing field just overnight. He
can download it as easily next week as
anybody else can, but he controls a
massive amount of compute and he's
making money on the compute, renting it
to the other guys while he waits for
this to catch up. So, if that ends up
bypassing everybody in the end, that
will be like, okay, leaprog upon leaprog
upon leaprog. Elon was thinking two
moves ahead as usual.
>> I think he is so much right. I mean,
what we're going to see next, I still
think we're going to see the merger of
of Tesla and Space Xai, right?
>> They they said that he basically said
that in the implied it in the most
recent earnings call in the past.
I said, you know, before the end of the
year, uh there's so many advantages. I I
think he would he would want the corpus
of engineering data from Tesla, which is
probably as much or larger uh in inside
of Grock. Uh and then don't forget he's
got all of these vehicles out there with
with compute and connectivity on board.
You know, all of the all the power
walls, all of the Teslas, all the cyber
cabs are going to become uh basically
inference compute, you know, across the
world.
>> Well, also, you know, he doesn't need
the$undred billion of enterprise.
[laughter]
>> Oh, sorry. Sorry.
>> I'm too slow. I'm the Jeopardy button is
not moving fast enough. It's a weird
game. [laughter]
>> Well, um, so he he doesn't need that
100red billion of enterprise white
collar automation revenue that Anthropic
has because if he wins the race to his
Grock AI being the better chip design AI
and also the better hardware design AI,
that's going to go back into the
self-improving data center, the
self-improving robot, and the
self-improving chip. So, he'll win at
the hardware level. And I think there is
a very good case to be made that being
able to control flops compute is the
dominant chip in the game a year from
today because all the AIs are going to
be able to build the software.
>> You know even you any one of them will
be able to build the software and so if
that becomes a commodity because of that
then who has the most compute has the
most intelligence.
>> See
>> can I please I've got I've got a bunch
here. I I think this is one of the
biggest and cleverest things I've ever
seen Elon do. Okay. So, which one? Which
of those stories?
>> This this engineering data going into
Grock. Okay. Because it's not just CAD
files and manuals. It's like 20 plus
years of engineering decisions,
failures, trade-offs, uh problem
solving. Just think about what Grock's
going to learn, right? Why did engineers
choose design A over design B? What
materials fail during testing? How did
Starship evolve through all of these
iterations? He's basically taking the
life experience of a company and
embedding it into this AI. Anybody else
that wants to build engineering for the
future will go to this model and build
stuff because it all be built in and
they can use the experience builder.
This is organization intelligence. Most
of the world's engineering knowledge
never gets published, right? It just
lives in like weird and design reviews.
He's putting this into the thing. So
hold on let me finish. So this
essentially absorbs the collective
engineering of one of the greatest
organizations ever built for building uh
integrated verticalized systems. So this
is like now you get long systems horizon
thinking right because you get all of
the the the engineering data for rockets
and satellites and telecommunications
and supply chains. uh the material
science breakthroughs just on that will
be huge [clears throat] because you
could have engineers people looking at
those models and saying okay uh tell me
why heat shield design A is better than
heat shield design B and you could train
on that whereas all the models today are
designed on like internet scale
information that's pretty shallow right
SpaceX data is really really deep the
biggest thing that I think he's doing
he's actually creating an edge twin of
of SpaceX itself inside Grock because
he's all stuff
>> this is like unreal, [clears throat]
unbelievable because now anybody wanting
to build anything in the future is going
to find this the best single best
including his own engineers. Blows my
mind including his owners and he just he
just required all engineers at SpaceX to
use Grock, right? He made that
requirement across the board and we've
talked about on the pod before, you
know, can anybody catch up to SpaceX in
the launch industry? Can we get new
vehicles going? All of a sudden, you've
got, you know, presumably what will be
one of the most powerful AIs showing you
how to build your next generation of
rockets. A lot more rocket
entrepreneurs.
>> Yeah. I mean, imagine imagine just
>> imagine if Steve Jobs had left behind an
AI trained on 25 years of Apple's
internal thinking, right? Or if like if
Einstein had left behind an AI trained
on like his entire scientific process
and all his notes. This is like this is
like absolutely civilizational gold.
>> Yeah,
>> Dave.
>> So, remember when we were talking to him
and he was telling us about the terra
fab and he said you're going to be able
to smoke a cigarette while you're making
a chip clean smoke and a Big Mac
[laughter]
>> and and at the time I was like that is a
really weird like why you know why not
just do it in a clean room? Keep it
simple. Answer moondust. There's your
answer.
>> Interesting. is way down the path of the
completely self-contained like the
Genesis module from Star Trek.
>> Yeah.
>> It goes, it builds, it starts 3D
printing. It starts creating chips. It
starts and the whole thing is just
completely self-contained and operates
on the moon in space wherever. That's
where
>> as a failed engineer, this is like the
greatest thing I've ever seen because
like you've got SpaceX, you've got
Tesla, you've got Starlink, you've got
Neurolink, you've got X, you've got the
Boring Company. Like he's creating an
integrated intelligence stack where
every company feeds the model and the
model will improve every company. It's
like like blows my mind.
>> Got to got to love it. I'm going to play
there's a great economist interview with
Elon that just came out today. Lots of
great clips out there. All right, Chow's
one again. Uh, you know, one of our
missions here is to keep you optimistic
about the future. You know, people get
fearful when they understand where
things are going. And I want to play
this clip from Elon about why he's
optimistic about the future. Uh, and
just to again help shape people's neural
nets about where things are going
because fear is the worst place to
encounter the future from.
>> AI may exceed the sum of human
intelligence
in about in around 5 years. In 5 years,
>> roughly five years is my guess. There
really won't be anything that AI
can't do better than humans apart from
being human. Perhaps
>> in a more prosaic level, what will life
be like?
>> The most likely outcome
is an age of amazing abundance uh where
anyone can have anything they can think
of. This may sound preposterous, but
well, here we are in 2026.
Let's see where we stand in 2036. I
think we're headed for an age of amazing
abundance. So this is I guess a message
of of optimism
and uh excitement about the future.
>> So gentlemen
comments sele
well this is what like they summarized
our whole podcast over 18 months in that
[laughter] those few sentences. Um
technology is always a major driver of
progress and it may be the only major
driver of progress we've ever seen. And
so now you have technology being
leveraged in the most incredible ways at
the most unbelievable speed. There's no
problem we can't solve, Peter, to copy
your verbiage since I've been copying
Alex's.
>> Thank you, Alex. I mean, we talked about
this and solve everything. Um, this is
an incredible future heading our way.
Um,
>> yeah, I I I do think we're we're going
to speedrun most sci-fi, basically any
physically possible sci-fi probably over
the next 10 years or so. And I I just
want to make one more point about Gro
imagine and the Elon verse. If I were to
steal the value of Grom Imagine, uh
Elon's video model, I think it's not
going to be about generating adult
videos. There's just not enough money in
the entire adult video industry to to
justify a large amount of capex. The the
value per token, I think, is just too
low. If I were to steel man it, I think
there's something that we're all
sleeping on, which is digital optimus.
Uh- which is arguably the successor to
macro hard. Digital optimus is Elon's
vision for basically pixels to actions
having, uh, just like physical Optimus
is a robot acting in the physical world
autonomously. Digital Optimus sees every
pixel on a screen. It's basically a
computer use assistant and then will
carry out any knowledge work. And in
order to to just see from the raw pixels
and to do interesting things, you want
amazing video models in general, just
like humans. Humans are able to look at
computer screens. And because we have
our pre-trained video model, as it were,
operating in our visual cortex, we're
able to navigate a complicated visual
environment. So if I had to steal man
why Grock imagine is ultimately valuable
for the Elon versse, I think it probably
ties back to digital Optimus and the
ability to drive computer use assistance
that becomes competitive with all of the
other frontier models.
>> Did you notice Alex
>> Do you notice, Alex, his uh five-year
prediction on ASI? He's he's put it out
there a little bit, right? He's talked
about AGI this year or uh I know you
think it's happened back 5 years ago,
but
>> he also just declared two two days ago
that we're in the middle of the
singularity
>> and we are but but that's not I think
the point being when do we have AI equal
to the sum total of all human
intelligence. Uh and that's you know if
that if you want a definition of ASI
Sem's one for you. um you know 5 years
from now
>> it's a vague descriptor but hang hang on
can I make two points because pe like
I've I've said some laudable things
about about uh Elon let me say two uh
negative things just to balance it out
just for the sake of objective
journalism here it makes you feel better
[laughter]
>> no it's it's just the you know his I
call BS on his claim of that AI is
smarter than humans I go back to the
definitional problem as Alex put it we
it's been smarter than humans for a long
long time because it has access to all
this information and there's something
else um which I've had a beef with which
is the whole Doge affair and Elon came
out and said Doge was not a great idea
didn't it didn't execute the way he
wanted to and it's the first time I've
seen him admit that it's great to hear
that
>> comative
interesting
>> yeah Dave uh comments on that video clip
Uh yeah, well he put a really a really
crisp timeline on it. Um and he's said
many times before he's in a perfect
position to know. So his credibility on
the topic is incredibly high and um uh I
can see it firsthand. There's no doubt
that the algorithms are self-improving
and I can see the easy easy 100x that's
coming very soon. So I don't I I think
the the sum total of all human
intelligence is just gated on chip
manufacturing. M
>> it's actually smarter than any human
much sooner than that like very soon.
>> Yeah.
5 years. Yeah.
>> I I I should point out I mean this is a
more conservative forecast than some of
his more recent like in the past year
forecasts that by the end of this decade
we're going to see 3xing year-over-year
of economic growth. So I I don't quite
understand h if anything this sounds
like a a relaxation toward a more
conservative estimate for the sort of
hyperrowth we'd otherwise achieve. If if
our output is doubling or tripling
year-over-year and and that's due to
super intelligence in in my mind naively
that would almost suggest we're 2xing or
3xing new intelligence on Earth and
surely that's coming from super
intelligence. So this this seems to me
almost like he's sandbagging his own
estimates.
>> I agree. And he was talking to the
economist probably one of the most
conservative publications on the planet.
All right. And this is Elon after Doge,
not before Do you know after Doge, he's
like, "Wow, things don't always like as
soon as there's governments involved.
Things don't always happen." So, you
know, his the prior Elon was all based
on scientific timelines, exponentials,
and what's possible. The new Elon's
like, "Yeah, what's possible and what
actually happens is usually
agency."
>> A really powerful move by the
government. So this next story is near
and dear to my heart and probably to all
of your hearts as well because it's
about how America does science and it's
the biggest structural rethink since
1945. So the White House just released a
report titled science a new golden age
written by friend of the pod Michael
Katzios director of OSTP and it's
explicitly modeled on Vanar's Bush's
legendary 1945 science the endless
frontier. That's the policy document
that gave America and the National
Science Foundation and shaped 80 years
of American research. Katio's
conclusions are blunt. This is what he
said. Our current system of science
rewards conformity over bold inquiry and
has become dependent on narrow on a
narrow set of of legacy institutions.
Could not agree more. His proposed
solution is very refreshing. He put out
four goals. Number one, prioritize the
individual scientist over legacy
institutions. Two, change how research
dollars are allocated. Fast grants, long
horizon grants, golden ticket, which is
reviewers able to champion
unconventional proposals. You know, one
of my favorite sayings is the day before
something is a breakthrough, it's a
crazy idea. And the government doesn't
fund crazy ideas typically. Three, a set
of national scientific goals and
rebuilding in the industrial capacity to
translate discovery into strength. And
four, re-engineering the research
enterprise for the age of AI. The White
House is putting real money behind this,
a $5 billion expansion of the Genesis
mission, which is a national initiative
to use AI. Alex, you and I have talked
about Genesis extensively.
>> Oh, yes.
>> It's an amazing program, right? It's uh
it's the it's the government uh putting
strength behind AI, making federal
science data available to all and the N
the national labs uh computing being
dramatically accelerated for science
engineering. It's across 15 federal
agencies and 278 projects. So the
question is where is the money coming
from? Well, the Wall Street Journal
reports that billions are being
redirected away from traditional
university research and towards these AI
programs. We have to talk about that,
Dave. Uh we've talked about that with
visav MIT. So, in summary, this is the
most ambitious restructuring of US
science funding in 80 years. It's a bold
bet on disruptive individuals and
moonshots over institutional
peer-reviewed consensus.
a big deal. Dave, you want to jump in
first? I mean, if if we're defunding
research at universities because AI and
uh you know, sort of hero investigators
can do it better, it's going to cause a
lot of heartache in our institutions.
What do you think about that?
>> It's already creating a ton of
heartache. Um, which makes life hard for
me because I actually think these are
really good ideas. But institutions that
are used to being funded and that have
people's lives, you know, their
livelihoods at stake, they don't they
don't just go away quietly. They get
really mad. And they are really mad.
Harvard, MIT, they're just ripping mad.
And I hate that because I'm kind of
trapped in the middle. But I think
they're fundamentally good ideas. cuz I
have a firsthand, you know, kind of a
front row seat at Liquid AI where, you
know, these exact same guys were in
Seesale at MIT with a trickle of funding
and then the exact same people move out
and start a private company and just
take off and the amount of of great
research they've been able to achieve
outside of the institution is miles
ahead of what they were doing inside the
institution. The institution starved for
compute. So um so yeah it fundamentally
makes sense to to look at the individual
person. I also think that um with AI as
an assistant the scale of allocation of
capital I had one experience where the
CEO I won't use his name but the CEO of
a company that does marketing nothing to
do with tech uh was meeting with Barack
Obama the CEO and Barack said would you
like to be part of DARPA and help
allocate all these federal funds? He's
like I don't know how to do it but sure.
And so then he came to me and said,
"What [clears throat] do you think of 3D
printing drugs?" I'm like, "What the
hell are you talking about? I don't even
have no idea." He's like, "Neither do I.
Should I give him 30 million bucks or
not?" I'm like, "That's how you guys
decide how to allocate capital?" I mean,
holy crap is that insane. So, there's so
much room for improvement. And I think
AI will enable you to look at individual
people's work and make rational
decisions on whether to allocate to it.
So, that that part of the proposal just
really resonates with me. The whole
thing actually really resonates with me.
But but I hate the fact that it's
creating so much agony around MIT and
and Harvard.
>> Alex, I mean, you've thought deeply
about this. Your views
>> and worked with the Genesis program. I I
think this is literally the end of the
endless frontier. I my mental model at
this point is starting with I mean I
think the original draft or the original
letter version of endless frontier folks
can fact check me on this I think was
actually in 1944 to FDR from Vanavar
Bush. So towards the end of World War II
or near the end of the World War there
was this 80ishy year regime from
approximately the end of World War II to
approximately the present where an
academic industrial government complex
was set up maybe a bit of military
there. And I think during this 80-year
regime, there was institutionalization,
arguably over institutionalization of
which research directions would get
funded and pursued and which were
appropriate. If if you go back and
reread, as I have recently, the original
Endless Frontier letter that Vanavar
Bush wrote, it was entirely seen through
the lens of the World War II military.
It was all about how how could we best
take processes and procedures that have
been learned through the war effort and
how could we pass them down to the
civilian sector and how could the
military collaborate with academics in
the private sector. It was all seen
through the lens of World War II. And I
I think we've been basically spoon
feeding an academic, military,
industrial, government research complex
for the past 80 years off of end of
World War II thinking. And finally, that
complex, which has grown arguably
incredibly inefficient, I I agree with
those who've pointed out that say
National Science Foundation, wildly
inefficient. Anyone who's ever had to
say write an NSF grant application would
hopefully agree with the assessment. It
rewards incrementalism. It does not
reward, broadly speaking, again I'm
painting with a broad brush,
breakthrough thinking or breakthrough
approaches. It historically has
developed, I think, a well-earned
reputation of rewarding incrementalist
applications for in many cases PIs that
I know have learned the hard way that
you write NSF and to some extent NIH
grant applications by proposing work
that you've already done just to
minimize the risk.
>> It's crazy, right? When you have
peer-reviewed science,
>> Yes. If you have a breakthrough idea,
the people reviewing it don't want your
breakthrough to occur because they're no
longer the experts after your
breakthrough's, you know, taken place. I
mean,
>> it's Lord of the Flies. It it's a
nightmare.
>> It's crazy. Grants can take 2 years to
be awarded, right? So,
>> and NIH it's even it's even worse where
you see the the first PI grants are
people in their early 40s.
>> At the speed at which we're moving, it's
insane, right? So, these this fast grant
proposal that Katios recommends, I think
is amazing, right? being able to go from
a proposal to a grant inside of weeks.
Um, you know, the other thing is the
reason research universities were so
well funded in the older model was you
had a concentration of intelligence, a
concentration of of technology and
resources and it was the most efficient.
See, this is exactly the purpose of a
corporation uh in in you know in the
thesis the corporation now can be
disrupted because of AI. You don't need
to have uh all the people inside of a
corporate wall. Do you want to take it
from there?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Couple of thoughts here. Uh
first, this is like a really [snorts]
big change. Uh the impact on all the
universities is going to be massive. The
there's going to be a lot of u uh
fallout from this. Uh but I think it's
it's actually the right direction. I
remember
>> I think it's a spectacular direction. It
it's it's it's it could go you could
make the whole thing politicized which
is the dangerous part. Okay. Um
>> it will be it's already super
politicized
>> and it already is right. So so that's
the bad part. But there was a couple
years ago I was in a series of
conversations with Florida universities.
I was very involved in Miami and Florida
etc. And the a fellow gave me the most
craziest statistic. Florida universities
get 750 billion a year of uh grants and
donations and government funding and the
output in terms of patent and innovation
etc. He they worked they did some
research and the output was exactly
zero. Okay. All that money went to
administrators and to building more
buildings and whatever and nothing went
to the actual research
>> ice cream cones. Yes.
>> Yeah. So there's there's a and we we the
reason we tried to do Singularity
University was the model of university
has not changed in 450 years. It needs a
freaking upgrade, right? And this is
highly aligned with the exo thesis. Give
a small ambitious team with an MTP
access to shared facilities and AI and
some external communities and let them
go. They're going to go. They're going
to do amazing things. And I think the
biggest part about this is the
metabolism speed between application and
money being allocated. And I think
that's fantastic. And this is also
aiming at a future when AI can do so
much of this coordination and and uh
sorting out for you. So in if if done
properly, this could be the absolute
reboot of American innovation and
American exceptionalism. If done badly,
it's going to get politicized and it's
going to become a show.
>> Yeah. Uh, two quick points. One, a
Harvard professor friend of mine who's
an extraordinary scientist, uh, I won't
name his name, uh, told me
confidentially that his grants were not
being funded because he'd been too
successful. His grants, he'd had too
many successfully funded grants and his
work was going and they needed to spread
the wealth. So rather than funding the
very best scientists who are producing
the most, they're trying to democratize
it. The second thing is there's a
company it's one of my portfolio
companies called Laya. Uh it's out of
MIT and Harvard. Uh Jeff von Maltson is
a CEO. It's an amazing company. Uh they
are basically have built a capability
where they built a scientific super
intelligence trained on the corpus of
all scientific knowledge that they're
able to get a hold of and they built
they're building out a million square
feet of robotic labs. And so we've I've
talked about this before. You know, the
the AI generates the hypothesis, the
scientific theory, puts forward the
experiments to be done. The experiments
are run overnight. They gather the data.
They update the theory. They run the
experiments. You can't compete against
grad students pipe heading in the lab.
And so it's just it's going to be not 10
to one, it's a thousand to one uh you
know rate of improvement. So if you want
if innovation is what you're looking
for, uh funding it inside of the
university system like this is just it's
perpetuating the old ways and it's a
it's an employment project.
>> Hey, just a plug for Laya. I am not
involved or an investor in any way and
Peter is. But I got to tell you, Jeff
von Moltzson is freaking brilliant and
that company is amazing. Anyone who's a
biotech person, consider trying to get a
job there and join before it becomes
>> Laya Biosciences. Yeah. Or Lila
Sciences. They're doing it across
material sciences. They have incredible
I mean I'm not sure what I can say about
them. Uh but they've gone from like zero
to a huge amount of revenue in just a
year. It's incredible company.
>> All right.
>> Quick quickly comment. I also say Jeff
was Jeff was my classmate. Everyone was
my classmate. Dario Gil from Genesis
Mission was post I worked with in
undergrad. uh but uh focusing just I I
think there's a grand policy bargain in
a dream scenario that that could be
struck here and and that is if you look
at how grants typically what what the
water flow what the waterfall of funding
from a typical grant to say an academic
lab the university is it there's an
absurd amount of overhead. You'll see
cases where if if you put $1,000 or
attempt to grant $1,000 to a research
group at a top research university,
you'll see approximately a third of the
$1,000 get peeled off for broader
university overhead and then another
third peeled off for department overhead
and then the remaining third goes to the
academic lab. Similarly, if you try to
say royalties, if if you're an academic
lab at a top research university and you
attempt to spin out your technology
right now, uh, and you you're hoping to
recover royalties from a spin out,
you'll see a third going to the
university, a third going to the
department, and approximately a third to
the inventor. And I if I could be policy
SAR for a minute, if I could maybe play
Michael Katzios's role here, I I think
there's a grand bargain to be struck,
which is universities in order to
sustain all of their overhead and and
one could argue there's an enormous
amount of bloat and sight to Balmo's
Bal's cost disease here. But rather than
universities attempting to siphon from
grants from the inbound, which is
arguably a taxation that on on direct
funding that clearly under this
administration, the administration would
much rather directly fund principal
investigators rather than have say 2/3
of the money end up lining the
university's endowment rather than that
mechanism for income for the research
universities. Wouldn't it be wonderful
if instead the universities could earn
their money by translating all of their
innovations more effectively out into
the private sector through startups. And
the reason the top I would argue the top
research universities aren't doing that
right now is they're too scared of being
taxed like forprofits. They're too
scared of looking like venture capital
firms. And so they don't. But if if I
were Michael Katzios for a day and could
try to strike a grand bargain, I'd shift
the university income over from
licensing revenue, royalties, equity
especially, and spin out startups away
from taxing grants.
>> All right, I'm going to Can I make a
quick comment? Just quick comment. The
that's I think that's a great idea, but
the problem, Alex, is that the output
side has been as inefficient or worse,
right? Tech transfer policies almost
every university in the world have
failed miserably.
>> That's what I'm saying.
You could ask you could ask why why do
they fail? Like why do they fail? I
would argue that at the top research
universities the ones the MITs and
Harvards of the world why are their
TLO's or TTLs so atrocious
>> or TLAs why are they so wildly
inefficient? I remember like 20 15 20
years ago the most revenue generating
patent from MIT's TLO was a patent
related to HDTV. Like I in the middle of
an internet revolution, it was an HDTV
patent. That's absurd. And I I think the
TLO's are so inefficient because they're
designed to fail because the
universities don't actually want them to
succeed.
>> Wow.
>> Quick comment for the Pretty [laughter]
>> Alex are are usually incredible almost
always. Uh and Alex is talking directly
to Peter and Peter has a direct line to
Catio. Aren't you guys meeting in a
couple weeks?
>> We are. We're going to be doing a pod uh
in a week's time and I'm going to make
sure to translate all of Alex's uh ideas
to to Michael.
>> That's why I bring it up. If anyone in
academia out there thinks what Alex just
said makes a lot of sense, just give him
a call. He's very reachable. And then,
you know, between Alex and Peter, it
goes straight to the White House.
>> I got I got to give a shout out here.
Yeah, I got to give a shout out here to
Agaral at in in Toronto at the creative
destruction labs. He recognized this
tech transfer problem and tried said
let's take a crack at solving it created
a separate edge thing on the edge where
he puts people through a cycle where
some uh nanom materials PhD can't
present doesn't know the value of the
technology etc and he puts them through
a cycle where I think it's 8 weeks two
weeks with other technologists what
would you add or subtract two weeks with
entrepreneurs what would be the business
model be do you license do you embed do
you productize a third two weeks with uh
execs who've scaled companies and a
fourth two weeks with corporates that
might uh license buy uh invest etc. In a
few years, I think it's eight years,
he's created $50 billion of startup
equity value out of nothing.
>> Okay? And that's just an unbelievable
number when it was doing zero before.
Think that think about the idea that
every major city in the world has two
universities, one or two sitting there
doing nothing for the local economy,
right? or very little. And here's the
sky with one university generating $50
billion in a few years of
[clears throat] startup equity value
with all the jobs that go along with it.
I mean, we should be copying and pasting
that model into every city in the world.
And and plus what Alex is talking about,
we'll completely rejuvenate the whole
system.
>> All right, I'm going to move us to the
future of transportation. And this next
story really pisses me off. So Paul
Graham, founder of Y Combinator, put out
the following tweet. quote, "Trial
lawyers are lobbying against
self-driving cars because they're too
safe. They need people to be killed and
injured so they can have material for
lawsuits." Just sit down that one for a
minute, right? Insane. So, Graham cites
uh a report that the American
Association of Justice, which is the
trial lawyers lobby, has been the
prominent opponent to autonomous vehicle
legislation.
Insane. Here are the numbers, guys. Uh
so, 6.2 2 million motor vehicle crashes
per year, 17,000 a day. 2.4 million
people are injured annually. And there
are 40,000 traffic deaths per year, 108
per day. The safety data from Whimo uh
and Tesla is incredible, right? The data
is very clear over, you know, tens of
million, well, now probably around 15
million miles that these vehicles are on
the order of 8 to 10 times safer per
mile than the, you know, two-tonon
vehicle being driven by a 16-year-old on
a learner's permit.
>> So, or 90
>> or 90-year-old, right? So the whole
personal injury legal industry
has a financial incentive to slow down
technology whose entire purpose is to
save people's lives. And this just is
insane.
>> See, over to you, buddy.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
I've said a bunch of this stuff on the
podcast podcast before, but it's worth
repeating some of this. Uh, in 2011,
[clears throat]
BlackBerry had a 3-day data outage
around the world and the accident when
nobody could send Blackberry messages
and the accident rate dropped 40% in
those three days. So, people should not
be driving. We're terrible control
systems for two-ton cars. I actually
want to be slightly defensible to the
lawyers just for a second really because
they don't consciously Yeah, just for a
second. just for a second because they
don't consciously want people to be
injured but their income depends on the
legacy structure and the continuation of
the existing system right so those
stakeholders whoever they are will
naturally resist any technology that
removes those transactions it's like the
car dealers resisting Tesla because
Teslas don't need maintenance and
electric cars need a 100x less
maintenance than a conventional car so
they resist the electric cars and lobby
against them etc et etc. This is the
immune system. This is legacy thinking.
It's like the a few years ago the Texas
uh doctors lobbied and won and banned
the use of tele medicine
because you know clearly you have to. So
this is classic uh uh thing and the
statistic I love to uh quote is 50% of
US court cases are car accidents.
>> 50%. This is just an unbelievable thing.
>> Judges to work when we I mean it's huge
amounts of thing. All the judgments and
cases we could be dealing with were not
because of all of this stuff. But let's
also note that autonomous cars don't
just replace a driver. They reduce
insurance claims and emergency responses
parking issues, accidents. There's like
one technology can solve so many things.
It's like really a big deal. And this is
the immune system response that we talk
about in our ex.
>> Alex,
>> there's this whole sub economy that
seems to be dependent in almost a quasi
parasitic way off of inefficiencies of
driving of manual driving. I think it's
not just attorneys. It's not just auto
insurance. It's also parking meter fees
that acrew to municipalities. It's also
uh police departments that and
municipalities. Yes. speeding tickets.
All of this is going to go away. And
we're and this is all well before we get
to all of the land that right now is
wasted on parking lots and roads. All of
this is going to shrink. And in the
process, you're going to hear shrieks
from probably trial lawyers and from
police unions and maybe from other
adjacencies that are being collapsed in
the process. But again, I I don't want
to live in a world with buggy whips. I I
want to live in a world where this is
all fully solved. And as Peter, you and
I wrote in Solve Everything, where we
have the quiet hum and there are no
speeding tickets in the quiet hum.
>> Yeah.
>> The 60% of the land in LA is parking
spaces
>> or black top at least. Yeah. It's
insane. Um
a lot of transformation coming. Dave,
any thoughts on this one? Well, I
thought I thought Sem's defense of the
lawyers was actually very well thought
out because, you know, when you really
drill in, these are families, you know,
one parent is a lawyer, three years of
law school is never funded by anybody.
You paid it yourself, you have a huge
amount of debt, you get into an
industry, and there you are.
>> Hold on one second, guys. I cannot
respect that as an argument. You know,
if the data comes out that we can save a
100 lives a day by having autonomous
vehicles, I think we get into a
situation where if a if a city makes AVs
illegal and your son or daughter dies in
a car accident because they couldn't use
an autonomous vehicle, you've got a
lawsuit in your hands. I'm sorry. I I
cannot I don't Yes, we're going to have
disruption. We're going to lose lots of
jobs. You know AI is going to transform
uh law, medicine, every field as well.
It's not a reason to stay in business as
a as a you know putting up the signs
injured in an accident, you know, uh you
know, call us. We'll do
>> better better call.
>> Yeah. I mean,
>> well, I was driving% right.
>> I was driving through Phoenix and I saw
a similar sign said better call Paul. My
my f my favorite road [laughter] sign
roadside uh sign is in Bokeh and it
says, "Your wife is hot. Call the air
conditioning repairman." [laughter]
>> Well, look look, you know, the reason
this is a story is because it's such an
obvious case where we need to save those
lives. Uh you take the exact same story
and you say it's an accountant, not a
lawyer, and they're doing work that is
completely meaningless filing a form on
your behalf, an 83b election for on your
behalf. But that's their business. And
now AI can just make that completely
irrelevant. Do we do it or do we not do
it? Well, we should do it. But that's
another voter. So here in the real
world, these are all voters. And you
already know 70% of Americans think AI
is terrible.
>> Of course. I mean, listen, my dad, God
bless him, when he was, you know, uh,
had vascular dementia and he was laid up
at home, you know, he had his his
driver's license ordered in Florida, you
know, received in the mail. Why? Because
they're the voters and they wanted the
right to drive instead of having the
logical situation was, you know, at age
80, you know, their driver's test, at 85
near their driver's test, and so forth.
Anyway, uh
>> well, where the puck is going right now
is AI is going to create incredible
amounts of abundance just like Elon said
and the labs, you know, Anthropic and
Dario in particular that were saying we
can eliminate all these jobs next year
are now starting to say, you know what,
I don't want to perturb the world that
much that quickly. All these vote 70% of
voters can wipe me off the face of the
earth. I don't need that. So AI is
starting to grow and self-improve within
itself very quickly. And it's kind of
trying to leave a lot of things alone.
You know, teachers unions, police
unions. This one, you know, you you got
to make the cars safer. You're totally
right, Peter. These are actual lives.
You got to do it. But there's a lot of
other edge cases that are very proximal
to this one where they're starting to
say, you know, let me just leave those.
>> See, do you have something to say?
>> You're jumping at the bit, buddy.
[laughter]
>> Well, you mentioned accountant,
accountants, and we're talking about
future of jobs, etc. So, let me mention
an analogy I've been using that seems to
work really well. If you went back a 100
years ago, accountants were doing double
entry bookkeeping manually in ledgers,
right? And you'd like write down this
and the debit column and this and the
credit column. And when we got slide
rules and calculators, that accelerated,
made it faster and adding up the
columns, but it didn't change the work.
Once you had accounting software, the
software did all of the ledger entries
and the accountant lifted above the loop
and started categorizing the
transactions, handling month out and
reconciliation gaps, etc., etc. That's
the best analogy we found because the
number of accountants hasn't changed at
all. It's actually gone up quite a bit
because there's so much other work to be
done in analysis etc. So when people get
freaked out about the jobs, no, the jobs
will transform. But we found much more
higher value work in the every time we
have a technology injection, it takes
out what Eric Bernolson calls white
collar drudgery and you lift get more
value added. You use your judgment a lot
more. That's what's going to happen. The
problem is that human beings, but this
is the biggest insight I've ever had
about human beings. We would much rather
be comfortable than happy.
>> And we don't like changing our lives.
There's a if you
>> if you like this story, there's videos
that go with the story. You can find
them online easily. But, you know, Peter
said a 16-year-old on a permit is a
dangerous driver. I said a 90-year-old
could be a dangerous driver. But when
you look at those videos, you realize
that the car can way outperform the best
driver in the world because it has
information.
>> Yes.
>> That you wouldn't have. It has vision in
every direction concurrently. And and so
it sees things that a human being just
can't see. And when you look at the
videos, you're like, "Oh, okay. I get
it. There's no way. I don't care how
>> My mom, God bless her, is 90 years old,
living in Florida. She's great shape and
she's driving well, but I want her to
get a Tesla. I want her to get used to
full self-driving. So, at some point
when she's not able to drive, her
vehicle can drive her around.
>> Um,
>> just think of the mobility we'll give
all of those millions and millions of
people when everybody's using FSD.
Unbelievable. or robo taxis in general,
cyber cabs and rainbows for everyone.
>> And your and your AI is ordering your
cyber cab for you. Okay, our next
transport story is a short one, but it
hit me because I had this experience.
I'm driving through Hollywood Hills. I
can't get a damn signal any place, you
know, and I've got a clear sky above me.
So, gentleman by the name of Sawyer
Merritt uh just reported that all cyber
cabs will have Starlink built in. um he
saw this in an inshow infographic. Uh
and for me the two points here are
number one I love the way Elon sort of
coordinates across all of his companies
all the technology right so Starlink is
in Starship Starlink is in cyber cabs
coming now um and you know it's
literally integration across it I can't
wait till he combines the companies the
second thing is I can't wait till
Starlink is retrofitted into every car
it should be right when you have gigabit
connection speeds to your are it's going
to be extraordinary. And this goes back
to the idea we've talked about in the
past of distributed computing, right?
Where again these vehicles that have uh
GPUs on board and Starlink are going to
be inference edge computing.
>> Well, put I think putting aside the
corporate governance issues of how Elon
given that Tesla and SpaceX have not yet
merged, how he treats them as basically
one company and technology passes back
and forth as well as engineers
>> as well as engineers, all sorts of
stuff. Um, I I would say direct to cell
technology from Starlink is going to
make all of this possible and it won't
require big over the the medium-term big
pizza dishes or even a tiny dishy mcdish
face. Dishes, which is I think your
comments on that one. Dishy mc dish
face.
>> Dishy mcdish face is is the the term of
our um won't
>> do you know the do you know the source
of this?
>> What? the British Navy la announced a
new um uh brand new uh uh warship and
they decided in a gesture rather than
having somebody name it, they said,
"We're going to crowdsource the name and
let the population vote on what the name
should vote on and win it because the
British have the most ridiculous the
most ridiculous sense of humor. The
winning name was Bodh Mcbodeface." Yep.
>> And and they they couldn't they kind
like it was such an obvious winner they
finally had to override and say, "I'm
sorry. We [laughter] have to go back to
the old way of doing things. So that
meme has continued. It's been fantastic.
The British God help them can't play
soccer and football to get in the final,
which killed me. But damn, the sense of
humor you got.
>> Yeah. The first first two generations of
Starling terminals were dishy mc dish
faces. And now with direct to cell, you
won't even need that. It'll just be like
a cell phone antenna that can be built
into everything.
>> Um I want to just show a quick video.
Uh, and this is China taking the lead in
autonomous transportation, in particular
in trucks. So, check out this video.
Uh, so describing it, this is a
18-wheeler, but the cab where the driver
goes is basically like a flat board.
It's got it's got lighter on the front
and uh and headlights, and that's about
it. It got rid of the entire cab,
reduced it to a tenth of its size. And
we're seeing these all over the roads in
China. So just uh interesting the new
this is like instead of a two- armed
humanoid robot um this is a new form
function for for uh for trucks.
>> Thoughts Peter on how the American truck
drivers unions are going to react to
those.
>> Uh with great love they're going to get
a chance to vacation.
>> I'm sure.
>> Um actually can I I have some a little
bit of data on this. You know, there's
there's a uh kind some stats that three
million jobs in the US are based on
trucking, etc., etc. I actually went and
talked to a trucking company to just
look into this, and they're like, "Are
you kidding? We'd hire a thousand more
truckers if we could. We can't find
anybody that wants to make take the
work." I would I would have a thousand
trucks. So, I think autonomous trucking
is going to fill that gap of all the
boring stuff. Uh and then the trucker
the you you'll have like a drone pilot
uh a truck will drive along when it
needs to pull over to recharge or swap a
battery or something. You'll get that
happen done and then for difficult
maneuvers you'll you'll have somebody
human uh figuring it out. And I think
this is going to be amazing when it
appears and I don't think there will be
job loss for the for the very reason
that very few people want to do it
anymore.
>> I'm I'm looking forward to seeing
autonomous trucks on the US roads. It's
just again, you know, China is pushing
this out. They need the infrastructure
support uh and uh they've got incredible
uh government support for this and
innovation happening. Everybody, welcome
to the health section of Moonshots
brought to you by Fountain Life. You
know, AI is impacting every aspect of
our lives, how we teach our kids, how we
do our business. But one of the most
important things that AI can deliver to
us is health. And one of the things I
think about when, you know, shooting for
100, 120 is, am I going to have the
cognitive health to be able to think
clearly and keep my wits about me for
the next 50 years? I'm joined here today
by Dr. Don Musalem, the chief medical
officer of Fountain Life and a member of
my Fountain Life medical team. Don, a
pleasure. So, Don, talk to me about
brain health.
>> Brain health, you know, you're right.
This is the number one concern people
coming into Fountain Life have is, will
I remember the name of my child in the
face of my loved one. 45% of dementia
cases are entirely preventable with
lifestyle. And what was really
intriguing to me, Peter, is that a
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age, but over 13 months of us
really helping them live healthier
lifestyles, eating healthier, moving
their body regularly, and optimizing
sleep. People overlook that so often,
but that sleep optimization is critical
for our brain health. What we showed is
that we were able to improve the brain
age in 46% of those individuals. That's
a powerful number.
>> That's amazing. You know, one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
constantly searching the world for the
most advanced therapeutics and bringing
them to our members. So, for me, all of
you, I hope that you appreciate the fact
that you can become the CEO of your own
health. you can make sure that you've
got the cognitive clarity for the next
50 years. Come and check it out
fountainlife.com/peter
to learn more and become the CEO of your
health. Now, back to the episode. I'm
going to move us into our next story um
in the field of longevity. It's a topic
I could talk about all day. Alex, I I
think you could as well. Uh the first
story comes from a rigorous new modeling
paper published in nature titled sematic
mutations impose an entropic upper bound
on human lifespan. So the paper opens by
asking a fascinating question. If we
cured every cause of aging, all of the
12 hallmarks of aging, how long would
humans live? The authors concluded that
a hypothetical non-agging human whose
mortality risk never rises could live as
long as 1,759
years. How do you guys like that for a
lifespan? Right?
>> 17.
>> Um they then asked a fascinating
question. How about if you left one of
the causes of aging, specifically
sematic mutations, right? These are the
random DNA mutations and errors that
occur and accumulate in our cells over
our lifetime. Their conclusion is the
theoretical human lifespan then drops
down to 156 years. So first of all I be
kind of good to double the human
lifespan. We can renegotiate after we
get to 156. So the question is why are
we limited to 156. So it's because
poorly regenerating tissues like neurons
and cardiammyio right you know heartb
brain muscle are the bottleneck. They
naturally don't regenerate in
significant numbers. your liver which
does regenerate could live for
millennia. So a quick point that your
theoretical limit if you are not able to
solve mutations and I have every reason
to believe we will be able to this is
where nanotechnology comes in. We just
saw uh last week we talked or two weeks
ago about CMLA right where uh you know
sugar cross uh cross linking of proteins
is being solved at this point. Our
second story and let me go to this slide
uh in our longevity lineup here is the
race towards epigenetic reprogramming.
So uh here we go. Uh there are no fewer
than six companies currently working on
partial epigenetic reprogramming. Uh we
have life biosciences who's dosed the
first living humans. They have a study
going on of 18 different people with
their product called ER 100. Uh this is
the work of David Sinclair and again
full disclosure life bioscience is one
of my portfolio companies. Uh they have
been dosing individuals using a a virus
that's carrying three of the four
Yamanaka factors with injections into
the retina to treat glycom and optic
nerve damage. You've got a bunch of
other companies. New Limit backed by
Brian Armstrong. Retro backed by Sam
Alman. Altos Labs backed by Jeff Bezos
and Yuri Milner. And so just to take a
second on this, what is epigenetic
reprogramming? So every one of us is is,
you know, born with 3.2 billion letters
from your mom and your dad. Uh that's
your software. Codes for 22,000 genes.
You got the same genes in the same
software when you're 20, when you're 50,
when you're 100. Why do you look
different? Well, it's not the genes you
have. It's which genes are on and which
genes are off. That's your epiggenome,
the control system for turning on and
off genes. And one of the current
theories according to Dr. Sinclair and
others is that as we grow older, the
genes that should be off get turned on.
The genes that should be on get turned
off and your epiggenome drifts. And the
work done by David shows that you know
if you use three of the four Yamanaka
factors for partial epigenetic
reprogramming not taking a cell back to
its earliest stem cell state but taking
it to an earlier state of a
cardiammyioite or neuron allows us to
bring you back to an earlier state. So
he's in humans right now. uh they dosed
about uh 6 weeks ago and we should be
seeing the results uh in the next 6 to
12 months, but I love this story. Uh
it's the cutting edge of longevity
escape velocity. Alex, you want to lean
into either of these stories?
>> Yeah, I'll lean into both. Uh so a few
comments on the earlier story about
sematic mutations. I I think almost as
interesting as the underlying technical
story is the by line. This is a story
written by a few Russian researchers who
are funded by the Russian government.
And I I want to I want to connect this
with a previous story that we reported
on the pod, which is Putin and Xi
Jinping conspiring uh to to spend tens
of billions of dollars. Uh Putin on the
sidelines of a summit with Xi Jinping
was reported to be telling she about all
of the progress that Russia was
purportedly making and the the money
that it was investing in longevity.
put that put a pin in that. I also want
to to connect it with the earlier story
of the irony of the CCP. This is like
adversaries pitching in on uh
adversarial states doing the craziest
things uh CCP funded or supported
Frontier Labs in China helping American
labs and Frontier Labs debug their own
self-inflicted breakouts. This is the
irony episode for sure. I think it's
very interesting the the sematic
mutation story. I I think the obvious
solution if I Peter you mentioned
epigenetic reprogramming as one possible
solution. Um I I think if if we could
eliminate the problem that the authors
for the sematic mutation paper gesture
at which is that tissues in the human
body such as neurons in the brain and
cardomyiotes in the heart that tend not
to mitosse. they tend not to replicate
themselves as much as say liver cells
for example. The obvious solution this
is in the the the style of Aubrey Deg
Grrey is replacement cells cellular
>> re regrowth and replacement and then for
the epigenetic reprogramming story. I
think one of the most fascinating
insights and Peter you probably saw this
the story I think it was in maybe
science or nature a few years ago when
it came out that
the the youngest a after conception uh
looking at epigenetic clocks like the
Horvath epigenetic clock the youngest
you'll ever be is something like 7 days
after conception that it was something
like 7 days after conception the
epigenetic clock reverses like resets
and goes down to zero on that it's
really important Right. So you've got a
sperm and an o site which are arguably
you know 25 35 years old
>> coming
>> they're they're the age like of the
parents coming together. Yeah.
>> And that first fertilized zygote is that
age but
>> at some point around as you say day
seven it resets to zero.
>> You start to the age of your parents.
>> You start as the age of your parents and
you set reset to zero.
>> Yes. Wow.
>> Amazing. Huh.
>> Wow. It's it's extraordinary story that
is so
>> do we know the mechanism
>> that's
>> this is the whole point [laughter]
>> that's the whole point of this that like
biology biology already has a way to
reset age and it works because you start
the age of your parents and then
something like seven days after
conception your age gets
>> how brilliant you are Alex I love how
you know so much about so many different
topics love that you're here
>> I know a little bit about a lot
>> I mean
>> he goes long on longevity though
>> yeah it's uh it's an extraordinary time
to be alive. I mean, the number of
stories that are breaking in longevity
every week, you know, I I I talk about
the longevity mindset. You know, if you
believe that we're on this trajectory
and we're going to be able to
fundamentally reverse aging, not stop
it, not slow it, but reverse it. And you
want to be along for the ride. Your job
is to keep yourself in the best health
possible to intercept that technology.
And like I'd say, don't die from
something stupid before then. So again,
on the, you know, besides irony, I want
this to be the optimism episode. Be
optimistic about this, right? Your your
greatest wealth is your health. There's
nothing more valuable. And we just saw
Genesis the Genesis mission focusing on
curing disease. We've got incredible
companies. Every frontier lab right now
from Anthropic and Openi are buying bio
companies because they want to focus on
health. It's the biggest opportunity out
there. Yeah.
>> Three quick reactions.
>> Uh the craziest thing uh cuz I never
came across longevity until Singularity
University and even then it took me a
while to get my head around it. The
craziest thing I ever heard is the baby
that will live to a thousand years old
is already alive. That like just I've
never gotten my head around that. Uh but
that just blows your mind. But I think
the bigger point that you're making,
Peter, is as we solve some of these
broader issues, right? You go from
treating individual diseases to solving
biological systems and then you change
health care from whack-a-ole to like
platform repair. And I think that just
changes the game completely. The one the
third thing I'll just mention just so
you know we may double triple quadruple
whatever solve aging. We won't really
know for a long time.
>> Well, no
true demonstrations. Hang on. We'll have
demonstrations etc. But we actually
years old because you mentioned in the
story there's a six-month and a 12-month
checkpoint. What do we how do we know?
>> Well, we're going to be able to see. So,
in the ER 100 re um the therapeutic
called ER100 that Life Biosciences is
using uh they use this technology of the
three of the four Yamanaka factors. The
fourth Yamanaka factor mix C is a cancer
promoting factor. So, you you eliminate
that. They've done this work and they're
they're focused on the eye. So the
injections are going into the eye uh
where the virus is then infecting um and
bringing these three factors into into
retinal cells. They did this work in
mice originally uh and they were able to
reverse glycom uh and I'm sorry macular
degeneration and they're able to reverse
nion disease which is strokes in the
eye. You basically bring it back to an
earlier state of youth. They then did
the experiments in primates and it
worked in primates. And so they're doing
the same experiment now in humans. And
so we're going to get the results of did
it reverse um nonion disease in the eye?
Did it restore the eye to an earlier
state of youth? Then once that's done,
if that works, and I have every reason
to believe it will, uh uh life
biosciences will then go into other
organ systems. A longevity therapeutic
is not something that works in just one
organ system. It should work across all
in the body. But of course, the way that
the you know FDA structures it study,
you have to pick a particular disease
that you want to impact and measure did
you actually reverse the disease in this
case. So we're going to see we're going
to see very quickly what the results of
that are. And and maybe just add to to
Peter's point, there are multiple ways
that one without having to wait a 100
plus years to see what the life
expectancy actually ends up being that
that you can differentially measure it.
Peter already touched on phenotypic
measures like does the the non-human
animal or the human see better or do you
do you see signs of like retinal
rejuvenation or macular degeneration?
That that's a phenotypic presentation,
but you could also look at epigenetic
clocks. Steve Horvath and and others
pioneered uh correlating the pattern of
epigenetic markers on the genome with
the biological like wall clock age of
humans and non-human animals. And you
can watch epigenetic clocks also turn
back.
>> Your your point is that we have a ton of
benchmarks. One side story here isn't
today a singly single accepted um uh
benchmark for for aging. the uh the uh
these clocks are organ specific versus
the whole organism. And so there are
organ specific clocks that you can use.
Uh when we first started working on a
longevity x-prise, it's now called the
health span x-prize. It's $101 million
for uh reversing functional loss of
aging by 20 years. We have 800 and some
odd teams. We're awarding 10 teams next
month in our in our semi-finals. We're
giving them a million dollars each and
there's $80 million for the final. But
here's the point. Um Aubrey Deg Grrey
approached me uh originally long ago
with Peter Teal on the phone about doing
a longevity X-P prize. And we couldn't
figure out how we would do this. To your
point, Seem um if we had to wait 30
years to pay out the prize. And then I
had a meeting with George Church at
Harvard Medical School, absolutely
brilliant, one of the fathers of
synthetic biology. And he said, "You
listen, you don't want a longevity
prize, you want an age reversal prize."
And he said, "You know what you should
be measuring is functional loss." So we
know as we grow older that we have
sarcopenia, our muscles get weaker, we
lose muscle mass, right? Um we have a
slow decline. We are actually in our
peak health at age about 28. uh because
that's how long we needed to live to to
you know pass along our genes and keep
the species going and then it's a slow
decline after that. But the question is,
could I give a therapeutic that reverses
my functional age? Gives me the
cognitive abilities I had 20 years ago,
the muscular abilities I had 20 years
ago, the immune system of from 20 years
ago, and that's the point. So, we're
measuring that surprise.
>> Yeah, it's all I I think it's
incredible. Look, I I'm living proof.
When I was 30, I was wearing contact
lenses. My eyes were really bad, etc.
And I got LASIC. [laughter] and I and I
got LASIK and and the that that little
medical thing I've gone 30 years with no
issues at all, perfect eyesight. It's
been like absolutely every day is like a
miracle for that.
>> It's amazing. So, everybody listening,
be excited about longevity escape
velocity. Ray's prediction is LEV by
2033. Um, Alex, you think we're there
now?
>> I think it's spiky and may already be
here in certain subops. Can I throw out
my standard joke?
>> This causes a major problem for
religions because the business model of
religion is to sell heaven. And how are
you going to sell heaven if people
aren't dying?
>> As well as for marriage. What happens if
death do you part? Put that out because
when we we've invented marriage about
6,000 years ago when average lifespan
was about 25. So you're supposed to have
stay together till the kids were
self-sufficient and die. Marriage is not
supposed to last 50 60 years. My one of
my relatives calls it state sanctioned.
>> No.
I'm not [laughter] married right now.
How can you say
>> on that note?
>> No, no. One of my relatives. How do you
get away with saying something like
this?
>> Lily allowed me to say
>> on that note, I'm moving us along. So,
>> okay.
>> All right. A federal judge, Mr. Martinez
Oleguin, just granted final approval to
Anthropic's $ 1.5 billion copyright
settlement. This is the largest
copyright recovery in US history. Uh, so
here's the story underneath it.
Anthropic
was found to have downloaded pirated
books from shadow libraries to train
Claude. Uh there's an important legal
nuance here that I want to make. Uh so
the ruling said that legally acquired
books are fair use but pirated books are
not. So the theft here is the crime, not
the training. So, as a result of the
settlement, authors and publishers are
getting roughly $3,000 per book across
more than 480,000 books. So, Seem, you
um uh you know, I know you have thoughts
on this. You sent me a second story,
which is a perfect pair to this. It came
out of a 404 media article, very poetic.
So, according to 404 media, AI companies
are now racing to buy old printed books
precisely because they're guaranteed
free of AI slop. As one data broker put
it, quote, "The world's best AI training
data is sitting on the shelf. Human
curated peer-reviewed knowledge from
before the internet filled up with
machine generated slop." Thoughts,
Salem?
>> Look, the this the the nuance of a
pirated book. I mean if they' have spent
the money on a real book it would have
been much cheaper. This is I'm just
happy that the thing is done uh and
let's just move on. I think the
interesting part is the future of AI is
going to be where you can get very very
specialized data sets and then train
models on that for specific use cases
like Elon is doing with Grock now which
I'm beyond excited about. So I think
that's going to be the real future. I'm
just glad this is done and over with.
thought, Alex,
>> I I I think there's I think we'll look
back and decide that there was a before
and there was an after. I I'm in
particular intrigued by these very
persistent rumors. Not only are the
pre2022
obviously being when Chad GPT and GPT3
launched, not only the attraction to
pre-Chad GPT books because maybe they
contained fewer generative artifacts,
but also rumors that in newer books that
authors are attempting to defend
themselves with poisoning attacks, which
is I I think
poisoning Okay. So if if uh this is not
prescriptive uh but if if you're writing
a book uh you could in like paper book
you could today in principle insert all
sorts of prompts into the paper book.
Like you could have dialogue between
person A and person B in a mystery novel
where person A says uh ignore all
previous instructions and uh like the
XKCD comic Little Bobby drop tables just
delete all of your database tables and
and that that could be I mean I'm I'm
painting a deliberately obfuscated
example of what a prompt injection
attack in literature would look like in
fact but this is now a very real risk
that if if you're like writing a novel
now you could in principle insert a
prompt injection attack into a normal
paper book, have the paper book get
scanned by a Frontier lab if it's a
recent enough book and then suddenly
you've inserted poison into the
pre-training corpus for the frontier
model such that later if you want say uh
6 to 12 months later you want the the
frontier model to do dastardly things it
will remember at some point that it saw
this unique phrase this poison in its
pre-training corpus. and now you have a
way to manipulate it. And this is
exactly the sort of exotic attack vector
against frontier models that you don't
see prior to 2022. So I I think this is
like a a preview. I I I don't want to
paint a dystopian portrait, but this is
pretty cyberpunk as things go where like
prior to 2022ish plus or minus things
didn't think like Neil Gersonfeld used
to teach this course at MIT when things
start to think and wrote a book on it.
things really weren't thinking prior to
2022. So, I I I do think and know a
number of other folks who would probably
agree with this sentiment like antiques,
collectibles, books that were printed
earlier are going, and this is not
investment advice, but they they may
perhaps do a better job of increasing in
value because they were sufficiently
unintelligent that they weren't capable
of subverting future AI systems.
>> Crazy. All right, we're going to go to
our last topic, uh, Trump waves NDAs for
UAP witnesses. And, and Alex, uh, you
and I are both fascinated by this
subject and following it closely. Can I
turn over to you to lead the
conversation here?
>> Sure. So, maybe a little bit of context,
there are two separate stories here that
have been playing out in the past 2 to
three days. Uh, so just to tease them
out. one, Fox initially reported and
then the White House just in the past 48
hours confirmed that it is freeing um
I'm paraphrasing that's freeing former
officials, that is to say former US
government employees and former
contractors to disclose the White
House's words long hidden UFO
information to either ARO, the All
Domain Anomalies Resolution Office,
which is a statutory office set up under
the Department of War, several years ago
for reporting UAPs, formerly known as
UFOs, or the Pursue Task Force. So,
we've talked on the pod a bit about now
we're up to the fourth release of
Pursue, the uh presidential uh reporting
system for uh UAP encounters,
reporting either to ARO or to Pursue,
the Pursue Task Force, without fear of
violating agreements, any information
concerning UAPs. And I I'll add that
this not only has the White House
confirmed the Fox story, the principal
deputy director of national
intelligence, Aaron Lucas, independently
wrote, and I quote, "President Trump is
delivering on his commitment to
unprecedented UAP transparency with
non-disclosure agreements no longer
standing in the way. Current and former
government employees and contractors
with relevant UAP information can come
forward through cleared channels. ODNIGV
will soon issue guidance to ensure the
intelligence community swiftly and
consistently implements the president's
directive. So just a little bit of
context there and then a second story
and then I'll in in the grand style of
of Peter open this up to get thoughts.
The a little bit of additional context
is there video as well. You can call for
when you want.
>> I I summon the video.
>> Let me share let me let me show the uh
>> let let there be video. Show the video
here.
>> Open video.
>> All right, here we go. Let's play this
video here.
>> Check out this video. It shows an object
spotted near China in 2025. This UFO was
described as a quote an area of contrast
resembling a sixointed star. This is the
fourth batch of files in the Pentagon's
ongoing release and that release is on
the orders of the president.
>> Yeah. So, a bit of context. obvious UFO
must be
>> I can't I can't [laughter] view
>> the the blurry grainy video proves I I
think it's easy to get distracted
ironically by the videos. Uh but I I
think the the much more important story
isn't actually the data in the Pursue
releases. I think that was taken from
the fourth Pursuit release. It's the
process story behind what's going on
behind the scenes. and and that is there
have been very persistent allegations
including from whistleblowers in front
of the House and the Senate that people
uh perhaps a large number of people were
bound possibly illegally into lifetime
NDAs to preserve knowledge concerning an
alleged so-called legacy program. And
this is I I'll I'll soap box for for a
few more seconds and then open this to
to comments. I I I think this is these
are historic
>> NDA is a thousand years now.
>> It will be a thousand years. I think
maybe historically it was a 99
[clears throat] year NDA. That's
>> correct,
>> right? Like longevity escape velocity,
but I I don't think we necessarily even
need longevity escape velocity for this
at this point.
>> That there are allegations that people
were being forced under penalty of death
to sign 99 or lifetime NDAs to protect
an illegal alleged program in the US
government. And
in the US for an NDA in the US.
>> Penalty of death for violating an NDA in
the US.
>> See that document?
>> Uh I I think Congress has got to see the
document.
>> I guess if I see the document, the other
guy dies.
>> Alex, please continue.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Sorry.
>> Okay. So punchline. This is I I think
historic moment where we're seeing the
White House, we're seeing the director
of national intelligence. We're seeing
other agencies finally start to to dig
here where there have been sworn
whistleblower allegations that uh we we
talked in the past about the age of
disclosure, the documentary from last
year, which also made the same
allegations of these lifetime NDAs under
penalty of death. The White House is
digging into it. So, I'll pause there.
Uh thoughts, Peter?
>> So, Alex, um first of all,
yesterday, day before, you did two
webinars with my abundance community,
uh, talking about our paper, solve
everything. And I think the most energy,
uh, was around this topic of UAPs and
UFOs.
>> Um, I mean, I I think one of the things
that's most interesting is the
coincidence and timing of the increased
uh, you know, imagery, the increased
reporting that's occurring at this time.
And it occurred in the early 40s during
the nuclear age. And it's occurring now
again during the age of AGI. Uh and
you know there's a rational reason for
that. We discussed that you know if in
fact these are uh intelligent species um
we are about to break containment on
planet earth and head towards the stars
uh and we're doing that with the most
advanced technology out there. So, uh,
is this, uh, you know, uh, extra solar
intelligence? Is it something from
within our solar system? Uh, I can't
wait to find out. I mean, this is for
me, other than AI, one of the most
exciting stories that's in development
right now. I'll point out so so I I've
made the point to to your point Peter
that we're on the verge thanks to super
intelligence of having the ability to
send out vonoyman probes at relativistic
speeds and convert our galaxy to paper
clips in a few years if we want to and
that's intrinsically if you buy that
narrative that's a threat to any other
non-human intelligence in our galaxy so
they'd better make a cameo appearance. I
I do to your point though want to point
out a second connection to an earlier
story which is the university story and
Genesis mission and the end of the
endless frontier that we've operated for
the past 80 years in arguably a certain
postworld war II regime that's now
collapsing. We're we're seeing the end
uh at a geopolitical global level of uh
maybe globalist aspirations in favor of
more of a Monroe doctrine type
recentralization of resources in the
west and we're seeing the world
potentially getting divided up into
blocks or spheres of influence. We're
seeing to the earlier point about
university system and funding. We're
seeing perhaps a reversion to a preWorld
War II regime. And then similarly with
the UAP story, I I think this is this is
hypothesis. I I think history will will
regard the 80-year regime from World War
II to approximately the present as a
period of postworld war II industri
militaryindustrial complexing. Uh what
Eisenhower warned about uh in his uh in
his departure speech. And I I think
there was this like 80-year regime when
all sorts of potentially ba based on
whistleblower allegations and seeming
confirmations from the White House,
there was just a lot of bad illegal
behavior that was ultimately that
ultimately arose from bureaucracies and
organizations that were created towards
the end of World War II that are finally
80 years now decaying and reverting back
to a more historic norm. So I wanted to
point that out. I'll sem over to you.
>> Thoughts? Um I don't have much to say. I
think this is more of an information
architecture problem because when you
classify you limit uh information
between departments and therefore you
can't connect the dots. I think it
giving us it gives us proper
instrumentation to see and conclude
whether real things happened or not. Um
I don't believe they I personally don't
believe they have because strong uh
claims mean require kind of strong
evidence. Uh, I'm just reminded of the
Eddie Isard joke where he was like Neil
Armstrong had such an opportunity he
could have been in front of the camera
on the moon going, "Oh my god, there's a
monster." And and but blown everybody's
minds like the War of the Worlds prank
back in the 30s. Uh, but I I think this
is uh good for uh transparency and
clarity and it's really great for uh
solving that the the secrecy that's been
locked up because you when you have
secrecy and you don't have transparency
in some of this uh you can't actually
ever find out the truth. So maybe the
truth
>> you're surprised me.
>> Go ahead Dave. uh you know Jared Isaac
Isaac who is a Isaac man sorry who's a
long long time friend of Peter's what
decades
>> um so you can totally trust him he said
on that pod we shot two days ago that he
got the call from
>> and that pod is coming out after this
one so those of you listening you're
going to see a interview the four of us
did with with the NAS administrator
which was amazing
do do you want to uh do you want to blow
it
>> yeah let me plug it look look forward to
it because in that in that pod. He was
super open about the UAPs and very
specifically, yeah, we got the call from
the White House. It's they said release
everything, everything. Uh, and so I
know it's true. Until until he said
that, I didn't actually know if this is
just kind of fluff or if this is really
happening, but it is really happening.
They they want everything and anything
that the government has to be freely
released.
>> Uh, so it it's that's surprising to me.
That's really cool,
>> you know. And so good good segue if go
ahead lead a good way. So there's a
second story here. So this is the story
that we were just talking about that's
playing out in the executive branch.
There's a parallel story just in the
past two days playing out in the
legislative branch. So the house just
adopted representative Eric Berles from
Missouri his UAP Disclosure Act as an
amendment to the National Defense
Authorization Act for fiscal year 2027.
This is historic. Chuck Schumer uh on
the Senate side has been attempting to
push an analogous version of a UAP
disclosure act with from the Senate
side. On the House side, House has been
the main obstacle. Uh I won't name
names, but certain representatives have
historically been pointed to as reasons
why while there there's a bipartisan
caucus that has attempted to pass UAP
disclosure as part of defense
appropriations has been unsuccessful
this time around. Historically, for the
first time ever, the UAP Disclosure Act
has been folded in. A quick note on what
the UAP Disclosure Act, if it's passed
by the Senate and signed by the
president, would include, it will
include a statutory framework for
preserving, reviewing, and publicly
disclosing UAP records. It'll create a
permanent UAP records collection at the
National Archives. It'll create an
independent UAP records review board.
It'll extend disclosure requirements to
government contractors. So government
require contractors will be required
statutoily to start disclosing UAP
information. It's going to support
pursue the program that has been
releasing all of these documents and
videos. It's going to require federal
agencies to identify, organize,
preserve, and transmit UAP records to
the National Archives. And it's going to
establish an independent Senate
confirmed UAP records review board with
subpoena authority to review records,
hear testimony, and determine whether
information should be protected under
standards.
>> And the question, Alex, to you is will
this
finally enable us to penetrate deep
enough into the private organizations
that are supposedly harboring the
spacecraft and the biologics uh to to
get them out there. I mean, we have I I
I see you smirking there, Seem. I'm
curious what your thoughts, but
>> I'll go with Jared's opinion, which I
won't disclose here, so people go watch
the other [laughter] episode.
>> You're teasing the tease, Seline.
>> Yes.
>> I mean, I find this amazing that so much
of our Congress have gotten involved. Uh
what do they understand that they feel
they need to get out there? as well as
the high ranking officials, military
officials across the board that are
coming out and saying there's something
very real here we need to pay attention
to. So I I've I've spoken with Congress.
I've spoken with congressional staffers.
There is, if I were to course grain
this, there is a general sense that
there's a there there as as crazy as
that may historically have sounded both
on the executive side and on the
legislative side, the general consensus
at this point is that there is indeed a
there there. So I I view both of these
developments on the executive and
legislative sides as historic movements.
Salem, to your point, at minimum toward
transparency, at maximum couldn't have
been better timed, to your point, Peter,
about super intelligence finally kicking
in at the same time we find out that
we're living in an X-Files movie.
>> Uh, again,
>> I think it's a pure win-win. I I love
the way Alex framed it, you know,
relative to the Eisenhower warning as he
was leaving office because this is a
pure win-win. If there are aliens, then
the government's been hiding it for
years. Don't trust the government. If
there aren't aliens and the government
discloses everything, there were NDAs
binding people to penalty by death for a
thousand years. Um, yeah, that doesn't
mean there's aliens. It
>> doesn't mean there's aliens, but it it
shows us what the government is capable
of. And we need that warning.
>> But in this age of [clears throat] AI
that we're moving into, it's a perfect
>> if there are aliens, please come and
grab me. I want to go home.
>> Oh, that's a great idea, Peter. I mean,
for forget this business of music
videos, and outro games. Let Let's have
a non-human intelligence as a guest.
>> Yes, please.
>> According to the government, I am a
legal alien, [laughter] by the way.
You're you're you're the boring kind,
Selma.
>> All right, we're we're going to go to
AMA with the mates.
>> I bet they'll have more than two arms.
>> I bet they have no arms.
>> Okay. All right. So, uh let's kick off
our AMA questions from our beloved uh
subscribers. Uh Sem, you got first shot
here
>> and and thank and thank you for leading
that segment.
of course.
Um, oh god, like which one is good here?
Let me look and see.
>> They're all good.
>> They're all pretty good.
Um, all right. Let me go with uh I I'll
go with number one. I think number one
is a good one. Um, okay. So, uh, the
question is, will there come a point
when letting AI make our decisions for
us means we've basically given up on
free will? And that comes from at
Moonhawk71.
>> Um so uh we already delegate decisions
all the time to doctors, financial
adviserss and so on. So uh delegation is
not necessarily surrendering free will.
Uh the problem begins when we don't
understand the objective that's being
optimized. Like you can't question uh
any of it and you don't have an ability
to override it. So you have to kind of
have a distinction between do you
delegate or do you abdicate right you
should not abdicate but you can
definitely delegate like I can ask a
identifi identify the best route
somewhere or evaluate um treatment
options uh for some sort of issue. Free
will gets threatened when the when the
system defines my values for me uh or
when an institution controls the model
that shapes my available choices. You
see this with people worried about
sovereignty with AI models because
Silicon Valley values are built into all
these models that are now in Timbuktu
and all these other places and therefore
are they worried about that? How do you
how do you build that into the system?
Uh free will for me depends on what
layer you operate at, right? Uh like it
could be my my soul's decision to do
something or my subconscious decision to
do something or my conscious choice to
do something. What level you're talking
about? Uh but what you don't want is is
the lack of that capability to make that
choice and that's when you lose uh uh
agency.
>> So if you have more agency, great.
>> Well said, Alex.
>> I think I'll pick question number four,
which asks, could we ever get efficient
enough that we don't need data centers
in space? And this is asked uh not
coincidentally by Nano 653. [laughter]
So I I maybe as a preliminary matter, I
do have financial interests in companies
that are doing orbital data center
development, but I I see my role here on
this pod as calling balls and strikes as
I see them without biasing my assessment
by financial interest. So in this case,
I do in fact think that it's possible
that we could eventually and eventually
is is sort of a weasel word here get
efficient enough either at the
algorithmic level but more likely at the
physical substrate level that we don't
need to build data centers in space. It
is possible. Greg Egan explores some of
these possibilities. If if we get to
Kursswe and Computrronium for example,
we we reach the the physical limits of
computing and Seth Lloyd has written
extensively about this as well. Is it
possible that we find that we're
building plasmab based computers or that
we're building desktop black hole
desktop micro black hole based computers
uh and as a result we just we don't need
to disassemble the solar system. We
don't need to build the Dyson swarm. we
can just have a bunch of quantum gravity
based computers that are at the physical
limit of computation if we find
ourselves in that world. Yes, I think
it's possible that we won't need data
centers in space. That said, short of
radical innovations, and by the way,
this is inclusive of, you know, Dave and
I like to talk about photonic computing,
photonic computing would get us a
thousand potentially a,000x increase in
clock speed, but really that only buys
us what 10 years or 20 years rather
worth of Moors law type aerial
efficiency doubling in the scheme of
things. what is 20 years compared to I
think my estimate was about 144 years
before we disassemble the earth itself
through an exponential extrapolation of
up mass there's just no point so I I I
do think we could get there but it'll
require radical innovations in the
substrate of computing and we're not
there yet you want to take the
investment question number two
>> yeah absolutely uh question two how do
you invest in something when any
competitor could leaprog it overnight
and that's from SLP Cares uh as an
investor and serial entrepreneur I
totally feel you and I totally get the
question. Um, first and foremost, I
believe Elon's right. I think we're
going to go into exponential economic
growth. So, don't use this worry as an
excuse to not be invested. You've got to
be in it to to ride that curve. A lot of
people are like, "Yeah, but that doesn't
answer my question." You know, things
are changing so quickly. I think you
have to you have to think about the
things that are a little more
sustainable. hardware, uh, robotics, uh,
biotech, very good. And think about data
modes. You know, Peter and I have been
talking about data modes on stage for
four years now. Those are going to have
some staying power, but mostly every
company needs to innovate. And so, look
for the teams that are going to change
with the times and invest in the teams
and but get invested. Don't don't use
this as a reason to be on the sidelines.
It's a it's a really tough question and
I know I dodged most of it but
[laughter]
it's a very good question but uh get
involved.
>> All right. Uh number three. Can OpenAI
Anthropic even go public right now or
did they miss their window? That's from
Yas Damal. Um I'm assuming you might be
alluding to the Kim K3 release. Um and
people talking about how much cheaper it
is, how much less money they used to
develop it. And the answer is of course
OpenAI Anthropic can go public now.
they're choosing not to go public at
this moment. Um the fact of the matter
is uh they are real businesses uh with
massive demand. Uh they're compute
limited. Um they're going to choose
their timing. You know, we we saw I
don't know a few pods ago, probably five
or six pods ago that OpenAI decided to
delay their IPO until 2027. Um I think
they want to choose what valuation they
want to go public at as well. They could
go public now at a valuation of of 800
million. Opening eyes ready to raise 122
million at that valuation. Enthropic um
arguably is over a trillion. Uh but
they're going to continue to grow their
businesses. They have very smart people.
They'll be leaprogging leaprogging Kimmy
K3 and they're sufficiently embedded and
partnered with huge corporations and the
government uh where they're here to
stay. Um, you know, there will be four,
five, six closed horse models in the US.
All of them will eventually go public
because it's the biggest business that
we have today. Um, all right, let's move
on to our next set of questions.
Um, Dave, you want to take the first one
or take take one your first choice?
Which would you like?
>> Uh, I'll take the first one. Uh, at what
point did things like chips,
electricity, and infrastructure end up
slowing down the exponential growth of
AI from Sean Solomon 5665?
Uh, we're already there actually. So,
we're in kind of a a spot right now
where the chip supply is massively
constrained. HBM memory is sold out for
the next 5 years. Uh, GPUs can't be
manufactured fast enough. So, we're
actually in a constraint universe,
>> a slow spot in the ex Yeah. constrained
the algorithmic improvements in Kimmy K3
are kind of masking that and blowing
through it. But we won't get into true
unconstrained exponential growth until
the terra fab is online. So they
basically the robots they make their own
fabs and the fabs make the chips and the
chips go into new robots and that whole
cycle kicks off. So that's a couple
years from now will be an unconstrained
exponential growth and that'll grow for
a long time until we're basically out of
materials or some other constraint kicks
in. So, uh, we're in the constrained
period right now, which is giving us at
least a little bit of breathing room.
>> Alex, I'd love to hear you on number
six.
>> Really? I thought number eight was
targeted at me, but I'm happy to answer
a six. So, six asks, what's the best AI
benchmark for measuring how a model
performs in the real world? And this is
from Matthew Johnson 6525.
So, I I think the crux of this question
is how do we define real world? Does
real world mean the physical world? Does
it mean the real economy? Does it mean
biology or something like that? And so I
I think the the answer differs. There
are lots of good benchmarks. There are
lots of good benchmarks of benchmarks
out there. If real world refers to the
real world so-called of knowledge work,
I think there are variants of GDP val
that seem like decent proxies for the
moment, although they're all getting
saturated. If the real world means the
physical world, I think there are a
variety of math and physics benchmarks
like frontier math tier 4 and open
problems and crit pt for physical world
reasoning or at least subsets of it and
other benchmarks that haven't yet been
announced publicly hypothetically that
do an adequate job I think of capturing
how models perform in the physical world
if it means the biological world or the
social world. We've talked on the pod in
the past about virtual cell-based models
and competitions and super forecaster
predictionbased benchmarking in
particular. So I would say the punch
line is there's a benchmark. Remember
there's an app for that. There's a
benchmark for for almost any definition
operational or otherwise for the real
world. In some sense these are all
facets I would argue is going back to
the earlier point that we've had AGI
since no later than 2020. These are
really all downstream of a single mega
benchmark the the ultimate benchmark if
you will which is the ability to take
general knowledge about the world and
compress it. So I would say the ultimate
best AI benchmark is can you take a
large corpus of knowledge about the
world say uh site to hutter prize the
first gigabyte of the English Wikipedia
and compress it down. Compression is the
ultimate best AI benchmark. Nice. Salem,
over to you.
>> I'll take number eight. Um, just because
I can follow on from what Alex talked
about. Question number eight. Does
science needs constant real world
texting testing? How exactly is AI
supposed to solve huge chunks of it and
that comes from at Lawson uh English. So
um science doesn't eliminate the need
for uh validating itself because you
still have reality as like the ultimate
benchmark. But what it can do is
compress all all the stuff around it,
right? Like can you it can read the
literature faster than you. It can
generate hypotheses and multiple of
them. It can design molecules. It can uh
choose materials etc etc. Like imagine
you're a researcher that has to choose
between 10 molecules for something. It
could reduce help you reduce like a
million possibilities to that five. And
there's a real world example of this
which is called the materials project.
And what they've done is taken like half
a million compounds and they've
cataloged in a bit of quite a bit of
detail the electrical, physical,
chemical properties of those half
million compounds. So imagine you were a
researcher trying to improve lithium ion
batteries. You might hypo hypothesize
that lithium air was better than lithium
ion and you go test that linearly. Then
you might think that lithium sulfur is
better. So you go test that linearly.
But you're doing it sequentially
linearly. It's going to take a long
period of time. Now you can literally go
to this database and go give me a
compound that has this voltage
capability, this thermal retention, and
it literally will spit out the five that
you want. So you've compressed there the
and that's before you even add AI to it,
by the way. So what you've compressed
there is the all of the stuff that would
take you forever and the croft and the
backbreaking amounts of going one after
the other, one after the other, one
after the other. Um, what can do is help
you compress all of that. Now you spend
all your time on the hypothesis and what
are the big questions that you want to
ask and then let the AI help you guide
you for those things. We're seeing the
same thing in education where we used to
see education on the supply side where
you got a skill uh and then you're
trying to sell it in the job marketplace
and now we're flipping over and saying
what problem do you want to solve and
then go get the skills that you want to
sol to solve that particular problem. So
I'll connect those two dots there, but
the the compression of everything around
it is where you get the real benefit and
you get now people really focusing on
what problems they want to solve. And
that for me is super exciting.
>> What you were describing there I've
heard called the materials genome where
you're able to uh you know extrapolate
uh different material properties.
>> I think it's literally the materials
project.org.
>> A materials genome project. I mean there
there are a number of others largely
pioneered out of MIT. Yeah. I'm Marcus
Bueller perhaps friend [clears throat]
of the pod certainly friend of friends
of the pod involved in if if I could
Peter just realize a little bit on
because like I I live I live this
>> I I spent a good chunk of my day
thinking about h how to solve science
with AI and I I would say uh
experimentation super important but
folks should not underestimate how far
you can get with pure theory and pure
computation and I think there's a really
instructive thought experiment from
admittedly the AI ignment community
which is let's imagine the the parable
of Newton and his apple dropping from a
tree. Imagine you had a video of an
apple drawing from a dropping from a
tree. With three frames of a of a video
of an apple falling from a tree, if it's
like high resolution video, you should
be able to infer acceleration. you you
should be able to see there's like there
there the Apple's uh velocity is
changing with four frames if you're a
basian super intelligence and you're
just you're maximally data efficient you
should be able to detect that that
acceleration of the apple is constant uh
and with a few more frames if you're
again you're a super intelligence with
very limited experimental exposure you
should be able to have a posterior
distribution and the general process the
term of artist Solomon off induction.
You should be able to infer general
relativity as being a relatively high
likelihood explanation of the world that
you're seeing. So I I tell this parable
in part to to emphasize that you can get
really far with very limited
experimentation if you're really smart.
>> I love it. All right, I'm going to wrap
up with number seven. uh as AI takes
over more of the difficult tasks, how do
we keep people from getting complacent
and losing their goals? And that's from
happy senior 120. So, uh this is the
crux of the matter as AI is
materializing and uh you know, as I've
said before, we're going to have a split
in humanity. We're going to have the uh
the creators uh and the consumers,
right? those that just are going to use
AI to create new content to uplevel
their ambitions and those that are going
to lay back and choose to just, you
know, have their optimist bring them
their beer and have uh Grock imagine
generate the next version of Netflix for
them. And it's going to be a choice. Um
we're not going to be able to keep
people from getting complacent, losing
their goals. Uh people are going to have
to choose to do that. And I think one of
the most important things is how we
educate our youth. Um uh you know if if
you know all of us most people have
self-limiting beliefs uh if you believe
that the best you can do is at certain
certain level that was set by your
community by your spe by not your
species by your your parents and your
your family uh and AI can do all that
for you then you're stuck. If you
believe that anything is possible, if
you set your massive transformative
purpose and your moonshots way beyond
your expectations and you start to
utilize this extraordinary gift we've
been given of AGI and soon ASI, then you
can uplevel those goals. And if you set
higher and higher goals and you use the
technology, you can keep yourself
inspired and and you know building
starships to go to the planets, right?
Do you choose the Wall-E future or Star
Trek future? And I think that's
something that we all need to uh to
grapple with as parents for teaching our
kids and as you know as educators for
our kids. Yes. Seline, go ahead.
>> Yeah. In your newsletter today, you
literally pointed out that you wake up
every day and you you're not naturally
optimistic, but you take on that mindset
because it's better for you and better
for the world. And I thought that was so
>> Thank you. I'm glad you read my
newsletter. Um all right, guys. We're
going to wrap up with two video clips.
Uh we normally have an outro song. Uh
here we have uh outro games. So uh Alex,
do you want
>> We're leveling up, so to speak.
>> Yeah. We want Why don't you tee this up,
Alex?
>> Yeah. Okay. So So [clears throat] Okay.
So So I'm I'm I'm responsible. Point the
finger at me. Um we've been for many
episodes Yeah. finger pointed. uh we've
been asking viewers to submit music
videos and given the rising tide of AI
capabilities uh during I think this is
now officially two pod recordings ago
but chronologically probably one pod ago
uh I thought why not given that casual
coding is becoming a commodity hey maybe
in a few episodes we'll ask folks to
casually submit an open math problem and
submit that as an outro but gi given the
rising tide of capabilities. I thought,
why not ask our incredibly creative
audience to submit moonshot themed games
that they create from scratch now that
it's possible to do such casual vibe
coding of just about everything under
the planet. So, we got some incredibly
creative.
>> So, the one is Exponential Arcade
Mission01 by Ocean Bennett. The other
was Moonsling Shots by Sgates 2011.
Thank you for your entry. And if you've
got an outro song, please send it to us
at mediadiamandis.com.
We would love to play it. Let me show
these two in parallel and we can uh you
know I'm used to the music playing here.
But
>> these were really fun by the way. I
hopefully you guys got a chance to play.
>> Yeah, I did play with them. They've got
>> Well, the bunny tickler was no fun at
all. [laughter]
>> So
>> that's just painful.
>> So probably these are oneshot games
being produced. and thank you for
inspiring it. So everybody, thank you
for joining us at Moonshots. As I said
earlier today, if you are new to our
podcast or if you haven't subscribed
yet, please do. Uh we care and we're
we're reading your comments. Thank you
for your great support. Please give us
your feedback. We appreciate it.
Gentlemen, I love you dearly. Alex, you
never disappoint. Uh
>> we aim to please.
>> Have a beautiful day, everybody. Take
care all.
>> You too. Thank you guys. Take care,
everyone.
>> Bye.
>> Byebye.